<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Replies made to the antiqueries of Thomas Lye, who writes himself minister of the Gospel at Chard. Wherein the parish-minsters, call, and maintenance, and divers other matters now in controversie, are handled and debated, by H.L. a friend to the people of God called Quakers.</title>
            <author>Lavor, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E934_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207677</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118999</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118999)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 140:E934[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Replies made to the antiqueries of Thomas Lye, who writes himself minister of the Gospel at Chard. Wherein the parish-minsters, call, and maintenance, and divers other matters now in controversie, are handled and debated, by H.L. a friend to the people of God called Quakers.</title>
                  <author>Lavor, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 71 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Dan. White at the seven starrs in Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>H.L. = Henry Lavor. Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lye, Thomas, 1621-1684.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118999:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118999:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REPLIES Made to the ANTIQUERIES OF <hi>Thomas Lye,</hi> who writes
himſelf Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Chard.</hi> WHEREIN The
Pariſh-Miniſters, Call, and Maintenance, and divers other matters now in
controverſie, are handled and debated,</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. L.</hi> a friend to the people of God called
Quakers.</p>
            <q>—Yea, they are greedy dogs that can never have enough, and
they are ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds that cannot underſtand: they all look to their own way,
every one for his gain from his quarter, 
<bibl>Iſa. 56.11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>For both Prieſt and Prophet are prophane; yea, in my houſe
have I found their wickedneſs, ſaith the Lord, 
<bibl>Jer. 23.11.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Thus ſaith the Lord concerning the Prophets that make my people
erre, that bite with their teeth and cry peace, and hee that putteth not into
their mouths they even prepare war againſt him: Therefore night ſhall be
unto you that yee ſhall not have a viſion, and it ſhall be dark unto you
that yee ſhall not divine, and the Sun ſhall go down over the Prophets, and
the day ſhall bee dark over them. Then ſhall the Seers be aſhamed, and
the Diviners confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, 
<bibl>Mic. 3.5,6,7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Dan. White</hi> at the ſeven
Starrs in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard; 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:118999:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118999:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>PARISH-TEACHERS</hi> OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>REfuſe not to think upon that day wherein ye muſt give an
account of your doings; when not others tongues, but your own
ſelf-conſciences ſhall be your accuſers and witneſſes; when not a
fallible and corrupt minded man, but God that cannot erre, ſhall be Judge.
Then will you not have leave to plead, what cunningly may be ſaid; but
ſhall what is really known, confeſs. Then will no witty gloſs deceive,
nor nice diſtinction have place: Now will ye be pained as a woman in travel,
and paleneſs will ſpread over your faces.</p>
            <p>But when eſpecially ſhall come to your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, thoſe
whom ye now do ſcorn, vex, and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly perſecute, the harmleſs holy
Lambs of Chriſt:<pb facs="tcp:118999:3"/>Then alas! what will ye do? how will yee beare,
ſuſtain how can yee the preſence offered of ſuch a thought as this?</p>
            <p>Now ſurely will your hearts be pierced as with arrowes, and the
horrors of death will claſp you round; and to dye ye ſhal wiſh, but death
ſhall flee from you.</p>
            <p>Thus I ſay will it be with you except ye repent in time.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="body_of_text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118999:3"/>
            <head>Replies made to certain Antiquaeries propounded by <hi>Thomas
Lye,</hi> who ſtiles himſelf Miniſter of the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at <hi>Chard, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Homas Lye.</hi> Anſwers returned to theſe Quaeres by one
of thoſe Miniſters of the Goſpel who in ſcorn are called
Pariſh-Teachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The very beginning
of this <hi>work</hi> is ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh't with an untruth, for I did not ſo call
them in ſcorn, but did purpoſely chooſe that word, as the which I judged
leſs apt to give them cauſe of diſtaſt. Yet this is a very meet
foundation for that which is afterward built upon it, ſo like they be one to
other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> To be left at the houſe of <hi>T. B.</hi> of
<hi>Aſh,</hi> who is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the fear of God ſeriouſly to read and
meditate on 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. <hi>They went out from us, becauſe they
were not of us, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>2</label>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes truly they
were of you, ſo long as (the earthly in them prevailing) they could take
Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſprinkle Infants, ſing <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms
in meter and wanton ſounds: but after that the eye of their underſtandings
was opened, and they turned from theſe Vanities to worſhip the Father in
Spirit and in Truth, then went they out from you indeed, and ceaſed to be of
your number, (being taken into a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118999:4"/>ſociety) even in
like ſort, and for like cauſe as juſt <hi>Lot</hi> with his family went
out of wicked <hi>Sodom,</hi> then ready to be ſeiſed on with Gods fiery
vengeance, &amp; wholly to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And now do they ſtand as ſo
many witneſſes againſt your falſe Call, and manifold deceits and evil
practices; what they know, what they felt in themſelves, the ſame do they
now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you teſtifie. Add hereunto this alſo, That whiles they were
of you, they were as ſo many Lillies among the Thorns for ſundry good parts
and vertues (which are wanting in you whom they left.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether thoſe whom God hath competently quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
with <hi>Miniſterial knowledge,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6. and <hi>utterance,
Col.</hi> 4.3. and who are ſolemnly ſet apart to the Office of the
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry with <hi>prayer, taſting, and impoſition of hands, Acts</hi>
4.23. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. &amp; 5.22. may be juſtly charged to run when
they are not ſent?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>3</label>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that is in
darkneſs himſelf, can badly ſee how for to turn others to the light; and
who knoweth not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther himſelf doth go, an ill guide will he certainly
prove in ſhewing the way to others. And who knoweth not God, 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ipſe notip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</hi>
               </note>
[himſelf] how can he well teach others to know him? And yet ſuch are all
they that hate their brother; that ſin; that are not in the New Covenant; and
ſuch (for theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) are you alſo, who are called of men both
Miniſters and Maſters; and this is even manifeſt to the children of
light, and ſhall moreover (in the progreſs of theſe Anſwers, as
occaſion is offered) be openly ſhewed and declared. What prayer and
faſting had ye when ye were ordained Miniſters? and what impoſition of
hands? was not the prayer made by them whoſe very prayer was <hi>an
abomination to the Lord?</hi> and the faſting, was it not of them who
<hi>faſt for ſtrife and debate?</hi> Alſo, the hands impoſed upon you
then, were they of other then a crimſon colour, as having been ſtained with
the blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jeſus? But to what purpoſe cited the
Anti-queriſt all theſe Scriptures? as though the uſurpers of the late
deviſed Ordination were men of the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, gifts and power, as were
the holy Apoſtles, who were<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118999:4"/>filled with the Holy Ghoſt,
who did and ſpake as they were thereof moved, who had the gift of tongue; and
other mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; theſe do we know, and own. But what are your Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Or
came at any time the voice of the holy ſpirit to them, ſaying, <hi>Seperate
ye me ſuch, or ſuch a one for the work of the Ministry?</hi> Alſo, what
gift do they give by their laying on of hands, which is to be ſtirred up? Is
it the ſpirit of Power, of Love, and of a ſound mind? yet ſuch a ſpirit
was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by, or with the impoſition of the Apoſtles hands, 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6,7. ſee alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 8.17. &amp; 19.6 Moreover the
gift mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the fore-cited 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 14. was ſo given
<hi>Timothy</hi> by propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the
Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: Are alſo your gifts (if any) thus received? Is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of
Propheſie aſſiſting, or converſant in your feat of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination? Do
your Elders at any time declare the truth of their Office and Calling by
healing of the ſick? 
<note place="margin">
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.</bibl>
               </note> And yet was
this gift and faculty annexed, or incident to the Office of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who ſuch
were truly, and indeed. Now ſeeing theſe things are not ſo with them,
with what kind of impudence then, or rather blaſphemous arrogance do they yet
aſſume and challenge to themſelves the Name, when they have in no wiſe
the thing it ſelf? but do lack not only all theſe cauſes that did concur
to the due creation thereof, but alſo all thoſe vertues, gifts, and
faculties that did accompany and ſhew themſelvs in the right
adminiſtration or exerciſe of the ſame; wherefore your Ordainers be like
to certain Impoſtors that profeſs indeed the true Art of Phyſick, but
cannot give a proof thereof by healing any one diſeaſe. Away then with this
<hi>faſting, praying, hand-laying Ordination,</hi> which was never yet
followed nor atteſted by a miracle, or any other viſible ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; tis no
better then that 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.19.</bibl>
               </note>
fig-tree that bare indeed leaves, but no fruit at all.</p>
            <p>Shortly after he muſtereth up a number of things, and calls
them, <hi>Doctrines by your Party a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>erted;</hi> to which I forbear to anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he having not
reſpectively cited the Books and pages where they might be found: In the mean
time it may not ſeem good proof that ſuch or ſuch a thing is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118999:5"/>truth, becauſe ſo ſaith <hi>Thomas Lye.</hi> Neither
ought it to be charged on our friends for error or blaſphemie if they
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times miſtake the meaning of words, they being in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half
unlearned, as alſo moſt of Chriſts Diſciples and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were,
whiles the learned Rabbles and Prieſts were bitter oppoſers and
perſecutors both of him and them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>5</label>
               <hi>T L.</hi> Whether thoſe
godly Prieſts and Prophets that lived by a ſtanding-maintenance, are
thoſe that are accuſed by <hi>Micah</hi> 3.11. to <hi>teach for hire,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here would ye methinks allude and compare your
maintenance to that of the godlie Prieſts and Prophets of old time: Firſt;
Where in all the Old-Teſtament find you this Epithet <hi>[godly]</hi>
ſtanding ſo near the word <hi>[Prieſt?]</hi> I am ſure it's a very rare
conjunction. Neither is your implied compariſon a vvhit better; theirs, that
is, the Prieſts and Levites, was a voluntarie contribution, and of God
himſelf ordained; your's a forcible exaction, and by humane Law, if any;
whereof more hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>6</label> Neither was this Querent vvell
adviſed when he ſcoffed at She Propheteſſes, (as he hath done) it being
a part of <hi>Joels</hi> Propheſies, <hi>I will pour out my spirit upon all
fleſh,</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and your ſons and your daughters ſhall
propheſie,</hi> &amp;c. Alſo, <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla</hi> was one of thoſe two
that inſtructed eloquent <hi>Apollos</hi> in the things of the Goſpel;
<hi>God gave the word, and great was the company of the She-Preachers</hi> (as
the <hi>Hebrew</hi> reads it.) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.11.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>7</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether Chriſt
hath not ordained, That <hi>they that preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the
Goſpel;</hi> and that <hi>they which ſow ſpiritual things ſhould reap
carnal things,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.11,13,19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To ſue men at Law for tithes, to recover
trebble damages, to diſtrain mens goods, and take much more then is claimed,
is this to live of the Goſpel? Did ever any Prieſt or Prophet in the times
of the Law, or any Apoſtle or Miniſter ſince the Goſpel, ſo live
either of the Law or Goſpel? Or will ye elſe grant us, That never any of
Chriſts Miniſters (mentioned in the Scriptures) did live of the Goſpel?
Is it<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118999:5"/>not much rather to be ſaid, That to live of the
Goſpel is to live of ſuch Alms and Contribution as men freelie give to
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as ſuch, and that vvithout the awe of any outward co-action,
terror of trebble damages, or other peril?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>8</label>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> We alſo live of
ſuch means as the Magiſtrate hath freely allotted for our maintenance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If indeed the Magiſtrate (or other) ſhall
give of his own private Goods or Lands to what kind of Preachers ſoever for
their livelihood, I have nothing here to gain-ſay: But if he ſhall give
them that which is another man's, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his conſent, to keep them in
idleneſs, I ſee not how this can be juſtified by the Scriptures, or by
any ſound reaſon. This alſo were repugnant to Chriſts own Otdinance,
name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the
Goſpel;</hi> and to live of the Goſpel is not to live of any inforced
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, as above is ſhewn; neither can you produce any one ſuch
Ordinance of Chriſt, that the Magiſtrate ought to take ſuch courſe for
the livelihood of his Miniſters. Now the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance above intreated, and to
which the Scripture cited in the <hi>Quaery</hi> hath reference, we find in
<hi>Luk.</hi> 10.7,8. <hi>And in the ſame houſe remain eating and drinking
ſuch things as they give, for the labourer is worthy of his hire: And into
whatſoever City ye enter, and they receive you, eat ſuch things as are
ſet before you.</hi> From whence I note theſe things: 1. That the
Apoſtles were to eat ſuch things only as were freely miniſtred to them.
2. By them who ſhould receive them. 3. Of their meat, who having a private
and proper right therein, ſhould ſo give, or cauſe to be given: Now
whether the men of your qualitie do live after this manner and rule, let all
ſober men be Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And albeit it were true that you ſowed indeed to your
hearers ſpiritual things, yet ſhould you not therefore reap their carnal by
force, muchleſs take them being reaped. Now what kind of Seed it is you
ſowe, doth by the Fruit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>9</label> Obj. <hi>But if we have nothing
allowed for our maintenance, but muſt depend of the charity of our hearers,
ſoon may we either beg or starve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118999:6"/>Anſ. <hi>Wherefore if God ſo cloth the
graſſe of the field, which to day is, and to morrow is caſt into the
Oven, ſhall he not much more clothe you? O ye of little faith! Therefore take
no thought, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, What ſhall we eat, or what ſhall we drink, or
wherewith ſhall we be clothed, for after all theſe things do the Gentiles
(or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then)</hi> ſeek <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.30,31,32,33. Now if ſo great be
Gods care of ordinary Chriſtians, how much more ſhall he provide for his
Miniſters, who are as it were his Embaſſadors, and have ſpecially
addicted themſelves to his ſervice? Are you his choice Darlings unto
bliſs eternal, and wil not yet truſt him vvith your bodies? Are you his
Labourers, and vvill not yet relie on him for your Wages, no, not though you
have his own word for it, and ſolemn Engagement? What greater infidelity then
this hath any of the Gentiles ever bewrayed? Neither can you avoid the Edge of
this Sword by ſaying, Your petitioning the Magiſtrate, indenting with the
people for maintenance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is no diſtruſting of God for your
live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood; foraſmuch as the proviſion God makes (&amp; hath made) for his
Miniſters Livelihood is by inclining mens hearts to ſupply their
neceſſities, and that out of their own private goods, and not out of other
mens, as elſewhere I have ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>10</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Then do men preach
for hire when they make hire their chiefeſt end, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea; and if they make hire any end at all, do
they truly preach for hire; Neither are we juſtlie charged to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench on
Gods prerogative in that we do judg you to preach for hire; for <hi>certes</hi>
that can be no part of Gods <hi>Secrets</hi> which is manifeſt to all men: By
your fruits are you known; Your ſuing to the Magiſtrate or Patrons for the
gift of the Benefice; your requiring of, and contracting with thoſe that
would have you, for great yearly ſums; and all this before you ſettle any
where to preach; alſo your late device of uniting of BENEFICES, but
eſpecially your remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings from place to place, even out of
<hi>New-England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> hither, for ſake of a better call,
and a lowder; that is to ſay, of a greater revenue; I ſay, all theſe
things fully inform us what is the end of your preaching, that we need 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118999:6"/>not to pry into your hearts to know that which is ſo openly
written in your fore-heads for every man to read.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>11</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether the
Scripture-ſaying concerning them that preach the Goſpel, <hi>That he that
ploweth ſhould plow in hope; and that he that threſheth ſhould he made
partaker of his hope,</hi> 1 Cor. 9,10 doth not allow ſome reſpect to a
maintenance for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Your plowing and your threſhing are of one
conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration vvith your ſowing aboveſaid? And plainly, this place is
not intended of any violent maintenance, nor yet of a State or Publike
Exhibition for Miniſters, as ſuch, which is the thing vve oppoſe. And yet
here would I not be thus underſtood, as if I vvere againſt a competent
Livelihood to be allowed out of the Publique even unto all men that be in
vvant; this in the mean time not omitted, That idle perſons vvho are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to
vvork, be compelled thereto. But hovv can you be ſaid to plovv or threſh in
hope of a Livelihood, vvhen as this is alvvaies the firſt thing ye make
ſure of, and get poſſeſſion of before ye ſettle to plovv or
threſh any vvhere? Now that which is thus poſſeſt or aſſured is no
longer capable of being hoped for: So your own Weapon recoils upon you, and
wounds you.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>12</label> It's very unlikely (what ever
<hi>Tho. Lye</hi> believes to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) That either the Hireling abides in
true Doctrine, (Can an evil Tree bring forth good fruit?) or that he which
preaches freely brings the Doctrine that's falſe; eſpecially, if beſides
his free preaching hee's ſure to undergo for his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſake all manner
of deſpight and perſecution. The Hireling is the falſe ſhepherd, and
how can it then be hoped he will feed with Doctrine that is true?.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether it be not lawful for the
people of God to dedicate part of their Eſtates for the Worſhip and Service
of God? And whether it be a ſin for the Preachers of the Goſpel to receive
that which is ſo dedicated? And whether it ſmell not ranckly of an
<hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi>-like ſpirit to with-hold that which is
ſo dedicated? Durſt you charge us, That though we feed our ſelves, yet we
feed not the Flock?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118999:7"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Tell us who they were, or are,
that thus have dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted part of their Eſtates, when, where, how, by what
mean and inſtrument, and finally, for what ſpace of time. Then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
demonſtrate that you are the men that have right to receive it. If this query
relate to any ſuch [ſuppoſed] dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation made by our Anceſtors in
times of Popery, I then op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Authority of a man well known by
hear-ſay, <hi>viz. John Wickliff,</hi> who in his Complaint to the King and
Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (Printed together with other his works, <hi>Anno</hi> 1608.)
<hi>Artic.</hi> 3. thus ſaith, <hi>Ah Lord Ieſus! where this be reaſon to
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the poor people to finde a worldly prieſt, &amp;c. is pomp and
pride, covetiſe, envy, gluttony, drunkeneſſe, leachery, in ſimony and
hereſie, with fat horſe and jolly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ah Lord Jeſu! ſith
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in few years men paid their tythes and offerings at their own
free-will,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>where it were lawful and needful that a worldly
Prieſt ſhould deſtroy this holy and approved cuſtom,</hi>
conſtraining <hi>men to leave this Freedom, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo <hi>Tho.
James,</hi> where he indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly maintaineth the Miniſters right to
tythes, alledgeth yet no ſuch dedication made by our Anceſtors, but is
forced therein to flye to the Analogy of Scriptures (as he calls it) where he
alſo confeſſeth, That the judgement of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Lawyers was, That
tyths were not due to any particular Church, before the Council of
<hi>Lateran,</hi> (which was yet a very ſandy foundation) but that men might
beſtow them where they would, <hi>Anſw.</hi> to 6. <hi>Obj.</hi> of
Parſons. In the new Law the paying of the tenth part is by a Law that is made
by the Church, that is (by the Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>Lib. de fund.
Legum. Angl.</hi> But before I paſs over <hi>Wickliffs</hi> teſtimony, I
ſhall for his greater Authority therein, note to the Reader theſe
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: 1. He was a man eſteemed to be of great and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found learning.
2 Of eminent piety, truth, &amp; honeſty. 3. He was himſelf a prieſt,
&amp; therfore not likely to have been diſpoſed to do or ſay any thing
unjuſtly againſt the Commodity either of himſelf, or the reſt of his
Order, but rather the contrary, &amp; ſo is here as a double witneſs
againſt you. 4 He is acknowledged to have been a man vvell skill'd in the
then Lavvs of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; ſo its not likely that he err'd through
ignorance. And fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>y, he delivered this his to teſtimony in Complaint to the
King <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118999:7"/>&amp; Parliament, to vvhom no doubt he was (as became
him) paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing careful, &amp; every vvay circumſpect, not to offer any thing
that might have ſavor'd of defect, either in knovvledge, or charity; or of
any diſhoneſt affection, or private end.</p>
            <p>Suitably to this Witneſs may it alſo novv be ſaid, that
there is no ancient lavv of this Nation, by vvhich the called Miniſters are
inabled to ſu for tithes &amp;c in any Court of juſtice or equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that now
is (the city of <hi>London</hi> &amp; liberties therof excepted.)</p>
            <p>And what then are they the better, if they have a Law, when they
cannot by Law attain the execution and benefit thereof; your ſuing in the
Exchequer is without all direction and countenance of Law; yea it is expreſly

<note n="†" place="margin">See Star. An. 32. H. 8. C. 7. &amp;
An. 2 Edw. 6. C. 13.</note> againſt the Law; &amp; alſo upon moſt falſe
pretences: As namely, when in your Bills you ſuggeſt, that you are
diſenabled to pay your 
<note n="*" place="margin">It may be 20. or 30.
<hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr>
                  </hi> a yeare.</note>tenths and 
<note n="*" place="margin">A ſmal ſum paid at their firſt
coming &amp;c.</note>firſt fruits, becauſe ſuch or ſuch a one,
with-holds from you the tythes &amp;c. when as many times it is but one man
againſt whom you ſo complain: Many times but a 10, or. 20 <abbr>s.</abbr>
matter that you ſue for; although you have both Glebe and Augmentations
beſides, to very great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues; and the reſt of your Tythes be quietly paid
you: (if ſo I may uſe this word, where a thing is not due.)</p>
            <p>Furthermore I demand by what good-right, or way of conveyance,
could our Anceſtors give away the Lambs that ſhould come of our ſheep;
the wool that ſhould grow on our flocks: our apples and ſuch like things,
which never were theirs to give, nor then were not yet in being; neither were
they capable of ſo much as being certainly known, whether as to their kindes
or quantities. Again, its in the choice of the owner of the land, whether he
will manure &amp; occupy it, or not: If he will not, then are there no Tythes
payable for, or out of it, which is a point conſiderable: For now, were it
granted indeed to have been in our Anceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors power to break, and tranſmit
into poſterity, the duty or obligation of paying ſuch Tythes, as are above
ſpecified; yet would it notwithſtanding remaine in our own power ſtil
wholly to avoid all effect thereof; and this without being lyable to be
puniſhed or queſtioned by the Clergy. Moreover, it is to be marked that our
fore-fathers who were Papiſts did<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118999:8"/>little intend, when they
gave their Tythes, that they ſhould go and redound to the maintenance, much
leſſe the luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Proteſtant Miniſters (ſo called) vvho vvith
ſuch cruel hatred and deteſtation they perſecuted even to bitter deaths
and torments: And one of our great &amp; ancient Lavvs ſaith; Let the will of
the giver be obſerved.</p>
            <p>But if the Querent reſpect to latter times; neither here do I
knovv of any effectual Lavv yet inforce for payment of Tythes. As for the late
Ordinances of Parliament tending hereto; its true, that they vvere able to make
a great noiſe, ſiting the Parliament: But vvhen once the Parliament vvas
diſsolved, they could not novv longer lavvfully be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. So you
ſee you are diſovvn'd both by Lavv and Goſpel, (ſo called) as to your
pretence about Tythes: vvhether vvill ye next go, ye vvandring ſtars; whether
will ye fly, ye Clouds without vvater.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning withholding of Tythes from pariſh
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, the forecited <hi>Iohn Wicklife</hi> ſeemeth not to have
ſmelt any ſuch <hi>Ananias and Saphira</hi> like ſpirit in them that
ſhould ſo do: For thus he reaſoneth in his complaint aforecited:
Therefore if our Prelates or other Prieſts whatever they be, 
<note n="*" place="margin">Blemiſht.</note>blecked by ſacrifice
of Maumetry, as with covetiſe, that is, openly ſacrifice of falſe Gods,
and other great ſins, as pride, Simony, Manquelling, Glotany,
Drunkenneſſe and Lechery, by the ſame skill (<hi>i.e.</hi> Reaſon)
Tythes and offerings ſhould be withdrawn from them by Gods Law and be given
to poor needy men at enſample of rightful <hi>Toby:</hi> and therefore it is
lawful to Pariſhioners to withhold their Tythes for open fornication of the
Curate, and turn them into better uſe: And much more they may &amp; ought to
withdraw their Tythes for great ſinns and open; as for Simony, that is
Hereſy (as Popes Law ſaith;) and for covetouſneſs, that is,
worſhiping of Gods, as holy writ ſaith, and for Pride, envy, and Gluttony
and drunkenneſs, ſith by Gods Law and mans Law God curſeth ſuch mens
bleſſings and prayers. And a little after; the firſt, if Curates do not
their office in word and in enſample that God commandeth, then their
ſubjects (<hi>i.e.</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118999:8"/>their Pariſhioners) are not bound
to pay them Tythes and offerings; ſince the principal cauſe for which
Tythes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings ſhould be paid is wanting, the paying of Tythes ſhould
ceaſe. Moreover in the ſame Article he thus determineth: But ſuppoſe
that ſuch Pariſh Churches (<hi>i.e.</hi> Benefices) were Lawfully gotten;
yet ſith they be ſuperfluous to ſuch men, the Tythes and offrings
ſhould be given to poor needy men; as St. <hi>Ierom</hi> and the Popes Law
teacheth. It ſeemes, the Pope himſelfe here to have been more modeſt, and
ſober, then to pronounce ſo black a Iudgement (as you in effect have done)
againſt them that with-hold their Tythes from the Pariſh Curates, or
Miniſters; for he alloweth the Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, when the Curate, or Prieſt,
hath ſuperfluity of live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to beſtow their Tythes to other uſes; and
this without purpoſe of enſnaring them in the guilt of an <hi>Ananias</hi>
and <hi>Saphira</hi>-like ſin; (or caſting them into priſon.)</p>
            <p>Concerning <hi>Moſes</hi> reſpect to the recompence of reward;
I ſay that between your reſpect and his is a very great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: His
was to that which was eternal; yours to that which is temporal: His was to
Heavenly glory; yours to filthy lucre: Neither is it to be thought, that
Chriſt would have ſtiled the falſe ſhepheard, an Hireling, if his
reſpect had been only to the recompence of eternal life (as
<hi>Moſes's</hi> was) and not chiefly to the Tythe of Lamb and Wool, &amp;c.
(as yours is.)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> T. L. whether thoſe whom <hi>Iude</hi>
condemns for runing greedily after the error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for reward,
were not the ſame with thoſe that periſhed in the gain-ſaying of
<hi>Corah?</hi> whoſe provoaking ſin was, as ſome of yours is, an
oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of and riſing up againſt authority in Church and State.</p>
            <p>An. If the querent had told us who this ſame were, that ſo
riſe up againſt authority &amp;c. He had done us ſome kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for
ſuch do we mark, and avoid. Now who they be, and of what colour that are
oppoſers of Authority in State, may eaſily bee knowne: Read but King
<hi>Iames's 
<note place="margin">the ſecond Epit.</note>BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SILICON DORON,</hi>
Doctor <hi>BAYLY'S</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118999:9"/>Hiſtory of <hi>Iohn Calvin;</hi>
but eſpecialy the relation of <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher Love's Conſpiracy;</hi>
and thou ſhalt find that there lodgeth in this portion of men, a ſpirit of
pride, ſtubbornneſs and rebellion, not much inferior to the
<hi>Jeſuites:</hi> Hereunto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may be added the 
<note n="†" place="margin">In his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſp. with
Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet.</note>teſtimony of <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> which is (as I remember) to
this purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> There is never any ſtir or rebellion in the
Chriſtian world, but they who be called Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel, are
chief contrivers [or Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters] thereof; 
<note place="margin">Where was your obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diene to Authority then, when
you not only refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take the Enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement, but preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aginſt it,
then you re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve days of publike Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving &amp;
Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</note> And this well know all Chriſtian Princes. And that he
did not here exclude the men of your Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may eaſily appeare, if we
but conſider the man with whom he hath there to do, and to whoſe reproach
he ſpake it. Now as to them that be called quakers, where and what
oppoſition do they make againſt Authority, both in Church and State? Is not
this indeed <hi>Nero</hi>-like, who burnt the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Rome,</hi> and then
laid the blame upon the Chriſtians? Name (if you can) one man of our way,
that hath done any wrong to others. Contrariwiſe, what kind of harme, and
injury have they not received from others, eſpecialy from the men of your
Function? yet when did they render evil for evil; when did your cruelty
overcome their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Thruſting, Beating, Haleing, and almoſt death it
ſelfe do they many times endure at your hearers hands and fiſts; and that
before your very faces, and even in your Solemn Aſſemblies: yet who of them
made ever any reſiſtance in ſuch caſe? or did open his lips ſo much
to revile? And is not both this a right Chriſtian ſpirit, and that ſuch a
one as the Devil himſelfe would be abaſht to defend? But wherin do ſome
of ours make oppoſition or riſe up againſt Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp;c.? Do they
not ever come, when the Magiſtrate ſends for them? and go when he bids them
go? or all the while they are before him (or elſewhere) do they do him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
harme in Body, Goods, or Name? Did they ever break priſon, or eſcape out of
Cuſtody? And for all thoſe inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they received &amp; ſuffered at the
Magiſtrates hands (which for multitude cannot be numbered) did they ever ſo
much as ſeek for ſatisfaction or amends againſt him? Now name 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118999:9"/>ye unto us on the other hand, of all your Party one only man
(if you can) whom ye may dare to match and parallel with theſe men for true
Chriſtian meekneſs and patience, ſo bearing all kind of wrongs, and as
touching the Magiſtrate and Authority for very friendlineſs and exact
obedience: Theſe of all men elſe in the world can better take wrong then
give it: 
<note place="margin">
                  <bibl>Matth. 18.22.</bibl>
               </note> Theſe are
they alone that can forgive their brothers offences, though again and again
repeated, though even unto ſeventy, times ſeven, they do at length amount.
In theſe finally, now after long death and utter oblivion, is the true
Chriſtian ſpirit and perfect mind revived again, and unto mankind
reſtored. No marvel is it then if they hear like ſlanders and reproaches,
and the ſame entertainment do find and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eel with the men of the world, as
alſo their Lord and Example, Chriſt Jeſus, did before them; He before
them was accuſed to have a Devil, to break and ſubvert the Law and
Religion; to have ſpoken blaſphemy, and many like crimes and miſdemeanors
to be guilty of: And the ſervant is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his Lord, neither muſt the
Diſciple expect to fare bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his Maſter did before him: But it's
like you intend their not putting off the hat, and refuſing to ſwear, to be
this oppoſition and riſing up againſt Authority, &amp;c. if ſo, then it
ſeems by your account, that <hi>Mordecai</hi> alſo (a far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Jew than
any or your Sect are Chriſtians) was guilty of like oppoſition and riſing
up againſt Authority, for that he in like ſort refuſed to bow to, or to
riſe before, or to do any reverence at all to <hi>Haman,</hi> the next man in
dignity &amp; degree to the King, who alſo had commanded <hi>Mordecai</hi>
that he ſhould reverence <hi>Haman,</hi> and that under ſuch a penalty as
threatned death to no fewer then to all the Jews in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. But I ask,
What is Authority the worſe, or how is it more empaired by a mans keeping on
his Hat before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, then if he ſhould put it off? Suppoſe
that no man at all would put off his Hat to another, ſhew us now what
miſchief or harm would by this means befall Authority, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if they
were in all things elſe equally obedient and conformable to Authority, as are
the people called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118999:10"/>Again, what is Authority
the worſe if men will not ſwear at all? Can civil Authority at no hand
ſubſiſt without mens yeilding obedience to the pride of man, and
diſobeying the Law of God? Now ſo confident I am of our cauſe, that to
your own very conſcience I appeal to ſay who they be that oppoſe and
riſe up againſt Authority both in Church and State, whether your
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riends or ours: Yours at mid-day,
and in open place doubt not to ſtrike, kick, pull, hale, drag and impriſon
men of rare innocency and of excellent vertues, that unto them had done no
violence; that do not provoke them ſo much by any unſeemly word or
geſture; that being harmed of them, do no harm to them again; finally, that
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves alſo both unto all theſe, &amp; yet farther
ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for their ſouls good, who thus miſuſe them: And all theſe
things have your friends doue, without either Judge, Witneſs, or ſo much as
Accuſer. Tell me now what is this to be deem'd but a kind of Rebellion, and
broad-fac't Contempt againſt the Laws of this Nation, and the Magiſtrate
thereof? But what had theſe ſufferers done? even this, Something being
revealed to them from the Lord, they ſpake the ſame in all ſoberneſs,
he that firſt ſpake having ended his ſpeech, and this in obedience to the
Lord, and according to the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29 30,31. And again,
are not they the very men that oppoſe Authority in Chriſts Church, who
break his Laws and Commandments daylie? who drink down iniquity as an Ox
drinketh water, and glory in their ſhame? and ſuch be moſt of your
friends and followers: Are theſe men like to be ſuch great friends unto,
and ſupporters of the Churches Authority? Indeed, without theſe your
Synagogues cannot ſtand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Where are thoſe warlike preparations? where
thoſe conſpiracies for devouring of them that differ from us in
Religion?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Read but the Relations of the late Wars in
<hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſpecially of <hi>Chriſtopher
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>oves
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſpiracy,</hi> and there ſhalt
thou find where the warlike preparations were: Read alſo the Law, or Bill,
made and contrived by the Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines,<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118999:10"/>ſo
called, and by rhem recommended to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and there wilt thou find
the conſpiracies for devouring of them that differ from you in Religion:
Moreover what may we term thoſe many Petitions that by the men of your order
were not long ago ſent to the Parliament? ſurely the aim and intent thereof
was for devouring more perſons than only <hi>James Nayler</hi> and his
Adherents; let the effects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be witneſs: Look alſo on the children
that ſince are born, and deny (if thou mayeſt) <hi>That a Prieſt was
their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> Who can it doubt that ſhall have once viewed and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
well their <hi>faces?</hi> So full of black lines they be, and ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of
malice; verily their ſullen and miſchievous counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance will not bear to
be gueſſed that they came and took nature of other blood then which runs in
your very veins: <hi>Pilate</hi> indeed condemned Chriſt, but 'twere the
Prieſthood that laid the plot aforehand: Theſe, theſe were the men that
not only as <hi>Authors,</hi> did deviſe ſhape, and preſcribe to others
the means, method, and order of betraying and killing Chriſt, but alſo as
<hi>Actors</hi> themſelves they did, and executed many things againſt him:
Theſe miniſtred as it were to the Ship, in which was imbarqued this ſo
nefarious deſign, both <hi>Wind</hi> for the motion, and <hi>Art and
Counſel</hi> for the ſteerage thereof and conduct. Be they any whit better
now, who bear the ſame Name: Oh how much worſe! Thoſe, that is to ſay,
the Jewiſh Prieſts, had for their proceedings the countenance of a Law;
theſe do all things [herein]<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>i.e.</hi>
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> contrary to the Law. Thoſe killed not
Jeſus till above thirty years old; theſe would have ſtifled him in the
Womb. Thoſe in one body of fleſh only; theſe in thouſands. Thoſe, for
putting end to, and croſſing their way of Worſhip; theſe for very
practiſing and being what themſelves profeſs and pretend to be: In ſum;
Thoſe, though they were the worſt of all Jews, ſeem yet to have been much
better then they who would be counted the very beſt of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118999:11"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>16</label>
               <hi>T.
L.</hi> Whether it be a ſin to endeavor to take the Foxes that ſpoil the
Vines? <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.15, <hi>&amp;c. Anſ.</hi> If all ſuch Foxes were
taken and kept in reſtraint, how many of you Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers would then be at
liberty? The Grapes of Chriſts Vines are love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering,
goodneſs, faith, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, temperance, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.12. Now where are
the Foxes among us that ſpoile ſuch Grapes as theſe? On the other hand,
What Congregation is there of yours in which are not plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Litters of
ſuch Beaſts to be found, except for their rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nature they be rather
to be named Wolves then Foxes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>17</label> And who they be that entice to
ſerve other Gods, wil then be put out of doubt, when as every man ſhall
receive accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his works; and then ſhall ſad tydings be to them who
now for a while are counted and called Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. We ſerve
that God who is worſhipped in ſpirit and in truth, who is light, who is
love; if other God ye ſerve then this, (for it may ſeem by your query you
worſhip not ours) it's plain that it is the god of this world, who ruleth in
the children of diſobedience; and therefore it is that in this world alſo
ye do receive your reward, the kingdoms of the World, and the glory thereof</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>18</label> Surely the Apoſtle in
<hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11. 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.1. (in the Query cited) did not mean that
mens mouths ſhould be ſtopt with a hand, or a fiſt, as the manner is of
your diſciples to do, with many a ſhrewd blow, and miſchief beſides:
Neither meant he any outward reſtraint or force whatſoever; for when were
the falſe Teachers mouths ſo ſtopt? it being as it were the lot and
portion of falſe Teachers in all ages to have the earthly powers of their
ſide, and all manner of favour, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, and protection from the
Magiſtrate, but they that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus ſhall
ſuffer perſecution, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>19</label> Neither did the Angel in the
Church of <hi>Epheſus, Rev.</hi> 2.2. uſe any outward violence toward them
who ſaid they were Apoſtles, and were not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as neither do
the people of God to the falſe Apoſtles now-a-daies:) But by <hi>not
bearing,</hi> 
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118999:11"/>here is meant <hi>not owning and
acknowledging, &amp;c.</hi> for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it's very abſurd to imagine that
this Angel did beat, whip, ſtigmatize, pillor, fine, or impriſon both the
falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles here meant, and the reſt that were evil, for theſe
alſo were not born, (as aforeſaid) which thing if you Teachers ſhould
once put in practiſe upon all your evil hearers, (and I think you count your
ſelves Angels) how many would you then have left for an audience? And it's
plain this Angel was not ſo much in favour with the ſecular Powers, that he
was able (if never ſo willing to have effected ſuch penalties on the
falſe Apoſtles and evil men; the Angels themſelves in thoſe times (as
now alſo) being of all other moſt obnoxious to the wrath and cruelty of the
Civil Power, as credible Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories do aſſure us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>20</label>
               <hi>T. L. Whether it be a ſin
to hate the Whore, and to eat her fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16.
<hi>Anſw.</hi> It is not to be believed you love the Whore ſo ill as to eat
her fleſh. Go curb thy luſts, vanquiſh thy affections, and bring them to
ſubmit to the yoke of Chriſt, and then ſhalt thou know the Whore here
meant, and her fleſh; till then thou doeſt but feed her of thy own fleſh,
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of eating of hers.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether we ought not to oppoſe
Popery, though (<hi>Jezzabel</hi>-like) it appears under a ſpecious
paint.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yea; but then ye muſt be ſelf-oppoſers: I
will not here ſay what a very eminent man feared not to preach, and that
before the Parliament, <hi>viz. That Presbyterie was in ſome reſpects
worſe then Popery it ſelf:</hi> See <hi>Peter Sterry's</hi> Sermon preached
before the Parl. on occaſion of the Victory obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the
<hi>Scots, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>22</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Becauſe many
evil-doers did not turn from their wickedneſs in the dayes of the Prophets,
Chriſt, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, was therefore their Miniſtry ſucceſleſs?
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.38. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If you Teachers had turn'd from their wickdneſs
ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny evil-doers as thoſe here mentioned in this <hi>Quaery,</hi> (one
of you with one of them compared) I ſhould grant indeed your Miniſtry not
to have bin ſucceſleſs, but rather of great effect:<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118999:12"/>But now if any man liſteth to know the ſucceſs of your
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and ſo to judge of this queſtion, let him but come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your
Meetings, and there let him ſpeak as ſoberly as he can, or elſe be
ſilent, with his hat on, &amp; ſoon ſhall he diſcern it may be with
danger of life, or limb, what ſucceſs your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry hath, or rather what
ſpirit your hearers be baptizd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: Who were they, I pray; &amp; what kind
of proof did they give of the Miniſterial ſucceſs, who ſtir'd up the
people, &amp; laid hands on <hi>Paul,</hi> being in the Temple, crying out,
<hi>Men of Iſrael help; This is the man that teacheth all men every where
againſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Law, and this Place; and farther, brought Greeks
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo into the Temple, and hath polluted this Holy Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e: And all the City was moved, &amp; the people ran
together, and they took</hi> Paul, <hi>and drew him out of the temple, &amp;c.
And as they went ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut to kill him,
&amp;c. And when they ſaw the chiefe Captain and Souldiers, they left beating
of</hi> Paul, &amp;c. Acts 21.27,28, and ſo along. And yet if (a few Names
only changed) this place were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed any where in <hi>England,</hi> would
any man doubt it to be meant and truly related of your <hi>Hearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>23</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Is it not an
Argument of matchleſs pride in you, thus boldly to condemn the whole
generation of the juſt that either have lived, or do yet remain in the Land
of the living, for evil doers, and perſons not turned from their
wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I never ſo condemned the generation of the
juſt, as this <hi>quaery</hi> implies; for my <hi>quaery</hi> had reference
only to your <hi>Hearers,</hi> whom when you ſhall have proved to be the
genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the juſt, I ſhall then confeſs your Argument; in the mean
time I ſhall never doubt to account them for a <hi>wicked and adul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erous generation,</hi> ſo long as I
ſee them with the ſame ill conditions as had they whom therefore the
Scriptures have ſo termed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>24</label> But unto what purpoſe have ye
mentioned the <hi>Noble Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and their fiery Chariots,</hi> as though you
with them had any affinity or conjunction? Verily you are the children of them
who ſent thoſe <hi>Martyrs</hi> in <hi>fiery Chariots</hi> to Heaven (to
uſe your own words) though you can novv adorn and celebrate 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118999:12"/>their memories as it were with <hi>garniſhed
Sepulchres,</hi> as did your fore-fathers alſo, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and
<hi>Phariſees</hi> towards the holy Prophets, whom yet in other bodies (as it
were) they had moſt cruelly ſlain: Like as your Anceſtors did to thoſe
you call <hi>godly Martyrs,</hi> ſo do ye now to the Saints of God ſo far
as you have power; and that you extend not your cruelty to death it ſelf, is
no thank to you; nor may it be interpreted as the voluntary bound of your
malice, as is well known.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>25</label>
               <hi>T.L. Shall all thoſe,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The way to heaven is but one. and a very narrow one; it
will at no hand receive the vaſt and ſpreading Compaſs of Tithes, Glebe,
Augmentations, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the love of the world, and luſts of the
fleſh; theſe in no wiſe can be gotten in, the waie's ſo ſtrait.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>26</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether,
ſuppoſing that <hi>Timothy</hi> followed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Paul,
viz.</hi> in meditating on that Word which he was to deliver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
as alſo, in ſtudying in the diſcharge of his Miniſtry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
he might therefore be juſtly charged to ſpeak viſions of his own
heart?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Timothy</hi> vvas an holy man, and <hi>holy men of God
ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.21. Alſo had
<hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> received a gift which was given by <hi>Propheſie,</hi> with
the laying on of the hands of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.
and the ſpirit of power, of love, and of a ſound mind. Now dare ye ſay,
(even he that is moſt arrogant among ye) That ſuch a gift, ſuch a
ſpirit as was in <hi>Timothy,</hi> ye alſo have received? The Bee can
convert into honey ſuch Juices as ſhe gathereth from Flowers: The Spider
contrariwiſe is ſaid to turn the ſame Juices into poiſon. Pick out the
meaning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timothy</hi> when he cited the ſayings of other holie men,
wel knevv vvhat he ſpake, his underſtanding and ſpirit alſo being
ſutable and commenſurate with the things he ſaid: Neither did his life
give his Doctrine the lie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>27</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether thoſe
that ſo far ſlight the Majeſtie of the great God and his Divine Oracles,
as upon pretext of imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate inſpiration, to ruſh upon them vvithout
premeditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Suppoſe ye that they vvho ſpake as the
ſpirit gave<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118999:13"/>them utterance, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4. as they
were moved by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. in whom the
Spirit of the Father did ſpeak without their taking thought how or what to
ſpeak, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.19,20. I ſay, did all theſe premeditate what
they ſhould ſay? and yet vvere they not therefore ſlighters of the
Majeſtie of the great God, and his Divine Oracles, as impiouſlie this
<hi>quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> (by conſequent) ſuppoſeth them to have been.</p>
            <p>Or think ye that they who were Chriſts Embaſſadors, did by
long premeditation &amp; ſtudy engender and compoſe thoſe Meſſages
which as Chriſts Embaſſadors they did deliver to others? The Woman that
ſpeaketh not without taking thought aforehand what and how to ſpeak, here
duty is (not to teach others, but her ſelf) to learn in ſilence. Go learn
what this meaneth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>28</label> To the following <hi>quaery,</hi>
concerning reading, quoting, and making uſe for edification the Books of the
Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, &amp;c. I anſwer, That he that is duly called to this
honor may take it; but unto you, thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>What have ye to do
to take my word into your mouths while ye hate to be reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Or can ye,
being evil, ſpeak good things? Or can ye propheſie when the Spirit of the
Lord never reſteth upon you.</hi> It was not for every one to bear the Ark
that had a ſhoulder; neither yet is it lawful to every one to ſay <hi>The
Lord liveth,</hi> although he have a tongue, and a voluble one too, left he be
found a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor even in ſpeaking that thing which is true,
becauſe not commanded, or nor meetly qualified thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>29</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether theſe
<hi>quaeries</hi> which you ſent us were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately inſpired<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or
rather, Whether there were not a conſpiracie among you for the inventing and
penning of them? &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Author of thoſe <hi>quaeries</hi> pretended
not himſelf to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel, but did direct them indeed to
ſuch as ſay they are Miniſters, and are not, but are found ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. Neither was there any the leaſt conſpiracie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us
for inventing and penning thoſe <hi>quaeries;</hi> neither were they glean'd
out of the Papers and Pamphlets of any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Leaders: Ye thought we were
ſuch ones as your ſelves; but our wayes are not like yours:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118999:13"/>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether it be an Argument of
covetouſneſs in an humble and orderlie waie, to deſire opportunitie,
libertie, countenance, and maintenance from a Chriſtian Magiſtrate for the
comfortable diſcharge of our gifts and abilities?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Chriſtian Magiſtrate will readily give
opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, liberty, and countenance to the Miniſters of Chriſt for to
diſcharge their Miniſterial gifts and abilities, though by them never
hereunto deſired, (will he forbid or reſtrain them) or elſe ſhall he be
no Chriſtian Magiſtrate, but rather an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian: And as for
maintenance, that will he alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them if their heavenly Father (as
Chriſt hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) feed them not, <hi>Matth:</hi> 6.26. But friends,
<hi>if ye ſeek first of all the kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſſe
thereof,</hi> (though you never in this humble and orderlie waie deſire of
the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate food and raiment) <hi>all theſe things ſhall be added
unto you:</hi> But you by not believing the promiſes of God, <hi>but
ſeeking after all theſe things,</hi> do openlie bewray of what gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
ye are, <hi>for after all theſe things do the heathen ſeek,</hi> Mat.
6.32.</p>
            <p>And here by the waie I cannot but this obſerve, That you who
with ſuch open confidence claim to your ſelves the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious titles of
Miniſters and Embaſſadors of Chriſt, do yet reckon your ſelves it
effect to be leſs regarded of God then the very <hi>Fowls of the air,</hi>
for theſe <hi>the heavenly Father</hi> (and not the Magiſtrate)
<hi>feedeth,</hi> (and rayeth too) <hi>Matth</hi> 6.26:</p>
            <p>Here alſo I do require of you to ſhew any one example in the
New-Teſtement, or any thing like an example, where the Miniſters of
Chriſt did ever once ſue the civil Magiſtrate for any of theſe things
mentioned in the <hi>quaery:</hi> But hereof more hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>31</label> Obj: <hi>There is as much equity
for a publike maintenance to be allowed to the Miniſters of the Goſpel now,
as there was heroto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the Tribe of</hi> Levi <hi>under the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1: The Levites were forbidden to have any
Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among the people, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2: The tithes under the Law were not onelie for
the ſuſtenance of the Tribe of Levi, but alſo of the ſtranger, the 
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118999:14"/>fatherleſſe, and the widow, that they might eat and be
fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.12.13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.29 So that the
ſtore-houſe for Tythes mentioned <hi>Mal.</hi> 3 19. had far greater
allyance and reſemblance to Hoſpitals and Alms-houſes, then to the called
Miniſters Parſonage-Barnes, and Places of receit <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An. 3. The man and his houſe were alſo to eat of the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes
or the proceed thereof <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.26.</p>
            <p>An. 4: The year of tything among the <hi>Iews</hi> was on the
third year <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.12. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.28.</p>
            <p>An. 5: The Owner of the tythable Lands was to lay up the tythes
within his gates <hi>Deut:</hi> 14:28: And not the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite</hi> to carry
them Captive into his own private Barnes; as now the called Miniſters uſe
to do: from whence, as to the relief of the ſtranger, the fatherleſſe and
the widow, (with many of them) there is no more return, then is redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out
of Hell.</p>
            <p>An: 6: The Miniſters of the Goſpel ought to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable
as wel in point of maintenance as in other things, to the ordinances, rules,
and examples, touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which are contained in the new
<hi>Teſtament,</hi> which alſo you do pretend to be your rule of life, as
well as of faith: Who ſo do otherwiſe, albeit they be called and counted
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt; yet is it manifeſt that they ſerve not the Lord
Jeſus, but their own bellies <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. where alſo they may read
their Doome: Whoſe end is deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And here I ſhall admoniſh the Reader once for all, that for
the moſt part in this controverſie touching Miniſters maintenance, I thus
have diſputed with the adverſaries, as men yet perſonating true
Miniſters of Chriſt: certainly my anſwers have equally concluded theſe
alſo as to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance here debated; whereupon it followes that though
all thoſe Scriptures &amp; reaſons above alledged were valid enough to
warrant a ſtate or publique maintenance for Chriſts true Miniſters; yet
will they ſtand our adverſaries in no ſtead at all, but be unto them as
broken ſtaffs, untill they alſo ſhall have proved themſelves to be
ſuch Miniſters, which is a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty no leſſe then for a Camel to
paſs through a Needles eye.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118999:14"/>T.L. Whether your Seducing Leaders may not be
as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged to ſcent fat houſes at vaſt diſtances (even as
farr as <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> from the North to the Weſt of
<hi>England</hi>) as Miniſters to ſcent fat Benefices?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> An. The Leaders among us (nor others) do not
break up mens houſes nor diſtrain their goods; nor finally uſe they any
forcible or ſiniſter means, whereby they may have to live of: But are
freely invited to thoſe thou calleſt, fat hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and there what is
ſet before them do they eat; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Luke</hi> 10.7.8. Do your
Leaders alſo do ſo too? No, yours are firſt to go in an humble and
orderly way to the Magiſtrate, for Warrant to collect and recover a large
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venew, before you eſpouſe your gifts and abilities to any particular
Flock (as you cal't:) Tis muck makes marriage with you.</p>
            <p>Think ye in your conſciences, that our Leaders, as you call
them, would have relinquiſhed their own Countries Habitations, Kindreds,
Callings, Eſtates, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things dear to men; for to travel ſo
many miles &amp; with ſo many difficulties to conflict, ſuch &amp; ſo
many ſcoffs, taunts, ſtripes, hurly burlyes, and tumults; ſtocks,
queſtionings, perils, and finally both long and greivous impriſonments,
voluntarily to undergo and indure, and all for ſake of a Fat houſe, or the
like? ſure, ye cannot ſo think; ſay what ye will. Although, (to retort
this matter upon your ſelves) it be not only thought, but even certainly
known; that whole ſwarms of the men of your faculty, have come out of
<hi>Scotland</hi> and New <hi>England</hi> hither, for ſake of our larger
Benefices; though its like enough they felt no great want (certainly not ſuch
a pinching one, as to make them ſtart ſo great way,) in the places where
they formerly reſided.</p>
            <p>But how much the men of your Coate, do prefer their own outward
eaſe, before the ſervice of Chriſt, is manifeſt by this; that on every
light occaſion, untouch'd, unharm'd, they croſſe the Seas, and away for
another Land; wherein they ſeem one degree (at leaſt) worſe then the
Hireling Shepherds in <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.12. for hee firſt ſaw the Wolfe
coming<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118999:15"/>ere he left the ſheep and fled; whereas your fellow
ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds haſt away, when as there is no danger in view; ſo far they are
from laying down their lives for their ſheep, which yet is the part and
property of a good ſhepherd, (<hi>Iohn</hi> 10.11.) Alſo what kind of
ſhepherds were they, and what title of honor deſerve they for their courage
who in the late wars, ſo unanimouſly left their flocks, and fled, not once
adventuring to ſuſtain the leaſt hazard, either for them, or with them:
Are not theſe rather Cowards then ſhepherds; and Mercenaries rather then
Volunteers? And yet of this ſort conſiſt your holy godly Orthodox
Miniſters, and renowned Champions for truth (miſcalled ſo.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>33</label> T. L. Whether there be not many
Miniſters (whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord is on high) that never ſolicited to obtain, but
were much ſolicited to accept of thoſe particular Flocks, over whom the
holy Ghoſt hath made them overſeers?</p>
            <p>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Even thoſe of
your order, that thus are ſolicited to accept your particular Flocks, I trow
they be not ſuch yet, as be content with the Lamb and wool, only of thoſe
ſheep, which (as in recompence of their Paſtors care) are willing to give
them theſe things; I believe their hands are of yet a far wider graſpe: Do
not even theſe your choice ones, your rare ones, your men for oſtentation,
Reap where they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Sowed? Spoile they not of their fleeces, theſe ſheep
alſo which never were accounted as of their Fold; but alwayes rejected their
care, and overſeerſhip?</p>
            <p>Neither did the holy Ghoſt make ſuch men overſeers; but
their own, and their followers wills, and deceit.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>34</label> T. L. Whether it may not be
lawful when the glory of God and good of Soules require, to leave a leſſe
and go to a greater congregation?</p>
            <p>An. Do ye not much more frequently go from greater to leſſer
congregations where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he profits yet
be greater? for who is there now ſo blind among us that ſeeth not clearly,
that all ſuch your motions and trudgings from Pariſh to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh do reſt
alwayes, as in their center, in places of larger revenue, then thoſe you
laſt left? Have you the boldneſſe <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118999:15"/>to deny it? I cite
for witneſſes againſt you, not hundreds, nor thouſands, but well neare
all the Pariſhes in <hi>England:</hi> As for thoſe Benefices, that are
poore and having little Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; are they not like a widow forſaken? Have
theſe their doores ever knocked at by you? exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> perhaps at a Harveſt time, or other good ſeaſon,
it be for your profitt (not for Gods glory, and good of ſouls) to viſit
them; truly you can paſſe by ſuch (how ſick and ill ſoever) as the
Prieſt and the <hi>Levite</hi> (your Anceſtors) did by the wounded man
going to <hi>Iericho.</hi> So that it may ſeem you account all mean
Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Pariſhes to be but flocks of Reprobates; and ſo not to be for
the Glory of God to endeavour their ſalvation; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to promote their
damnation; to make for the Glory of his juſtice: (as you ſomtimes
ſpeak.)</p>
            <p>T. L. Whether thoſe Miniſters at leaſt muſt not by your
ſelves be pronounced not covetous, that have either gone <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>35</label> from greater Benefices and ſate down in leſſer,
where the work has been more, and the reward leſs? or elſe have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
in leſser, and oftentimes refuſed the proffers of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</p>
            <p>An. How many ſuch Phaenix's can ye number among you? How many
ſuch black Swans? May not all of your Tribe that be ſuch, be conveniently
covered under a Buſhell, and this without lack of roome? It may have been
indeed, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in the times when tythes were in danger to be
abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, ſome of your brethren, being pretty well beloved of the
Pariſhes where they dwelt, thought it no part of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to change a
certainty for an uncertainty, though of greater value for the preſent: So
ſtill here was cheriſht the plant of covetouſneſs, though in a walled
Garden.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>36</label> T. L. Whether it be not a
ſlander caſt on many Miniſters in this Nation, to ſay that they indent
for a maintenance [An. Tis true that many of the called Miniſters do ſo
indent, and therefore no ſlander to charge it on many: Note here by the way,
Reader, the querent calls it a ſlander, to charge them with ſuch indentings
for a maintenance; If the thing be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be done, and agreeable to the
Scriptures (as moſt of <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118999:16"/>theſe men pretend it to be) why
do he yet call it a ſlander, if one affirme it of them? for ſlanders are of
things evil in their nature, and not of things Lawful to be done: This is
therefore no leſſe then an implicit confeſſion, that who ſo of the
called Miniſters, thus indent for maintenance, they do committ that which is
evil; ſeeing if this matter be charged on another, that hath not don it, tis
by them called a ſlander; That is, an evil matter falſly charged.]</p>
            <p>Further he ſaith—When as tis wel known many of them live
on a free contribution [An. Call ye not that a free con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution which men
yeeld unto you for fear of the Law, and of trebble damages <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
When they give you that, which if they refuſe, ye are ready to take by force
to their great loſſe and trouble to boote: Such a free contribution as
this, is, when a true man delivers his purſe for fear of the ſword or
Piſtoll.]</p>
            <p>Again ſaith he—And others very many preach hundreds of
Lectures <hi>gratis. &amp;c.</hi> An. And how many hundreds be there among you,
that take a ſtipend, or other reward for their Lectures? But who ſeeth not
this buſineſs of Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, is even become with many of you Preachers as
an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of merry meetings, and a kind of recreation? (To o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt other
ends yet worſe then theſe:) Moſt commonly the Lecture is but the ſecond
edition of a Sermon formerly preached, and for which ye were richly paid; and
ſo ye might well afford to give it away another time <hi>gratis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>37</label> T. L. For thoſe who in theſe
unſetled times, think it fit to be at ſome ſettlement with their people,
[An. It ſhould ſeem then it is in their own power and choiſe to ſettle
where they liſt, and are not at Gods diſpoſal to be ſent to this or
that place; as unto him may ſeem good: Made ye were Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters by the wil
of man, and ſo is the adminiſtration of your office ſuitable to its
creation ſtil in the will of man.] He addeth—Whether a prudent care of
providing for their own, and ſo not being worſe then an Infidell, 1.
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5 8. [An. If ye be of the flock of Chriſt; much more if ye be
his ſhepherds (as you pretend to bee) this prudent care is<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118999:16"/>needeleſs; for the Heavenly Father provides for ſuch; ſee
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: Neither is it lawful for you to ſhun this point of Infide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lity, by
taking, or begging other mens eſtates to provide-for your own, no more then
it is for a man being in want to take or begg an others goods of him that
cannot juſtly give them.] 'It followes—and fear of giving occaſion of
offence, if really forced to remove forwant of a competent maintenance [An. Do
we any where read ſuch ſentences in the Scriptures? Here hath the queriſt
in effect confeſſed, that their Removals (at leaſt ſomtimes) is for
want of a competent maintenance: What's that? let us be informed: Whom of
theſe Removers ſhall we take, as having defined unto us what, and how much
his competent maintenance is? Some have removed from 50<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi>
60<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> 70<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi>
80<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> 100<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi>
150<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> 200<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> by the yeare, to places
of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter profit. Now ſay that 80<hi>
                  <abbr>l</abbr> per Annum</hi> is a
competent maintenance (and I truſt ye will not deny it) all ſuch then, as
having this maintenance or a greater, did nevertheleſſe give eare to the
call of a louder Benefice, muſt needs be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of Avarice, love of
filthy lucre, and that by Judgement not to be reverſed, no, not in your own
Court of conſcience; ſo corrupt and partial as it is: Now how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch
there have been, is not my purpoſe here to recount; nor ſcarce a great
Volume would ſuffice to contain them; nor are their names worthy even to be
remembred; ſo many and ſo bad they be: Then ſaith he; 'As alſo the
feare of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God inſtead of truſting him, <hi>Mathew</hi> 4.7. [An.
There's no fear at all of Incurring Gods wrath by thus tempting of him; which
were indeed but to confeſſe his truth, and honeſty, by truſting to his
own promiſe; ſee before: But what makes this Scripture to the purpoſe?
Did Chriſt in that place forbid you, or the Miniſters of the Goſpel,
(while he reproved the Devil) to depend upon God for lively-hood?]</p>
            <p>It followeth—'Are not ſufficient grounds to induce ſome
Miniſters to procure a promiſe of a Goſpel lively-hood, [An. A Goſpel
lively-hood is, having food and rayment, to be therewith content; not to have
our luſts ſupplyed to all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and luxury, both in food and
rayment. But where do<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118999:17"/>we find this kind of bargaining for
Miniſters mantenance in the Scriptures? Indeed we do read ſuch a thing in
<hi>Micah.</hi> 2.11. The Prieſts thereof teach for hire, and the Prophets
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Divine for money <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo, we have ſuch Teachers
fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told in 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.2.3. But there were alſo falſe Prophets
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people even as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you, <hi>Who
privily ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies &amp;c. &amp; through
covetouſneſſe ſhall they, with fained words, make merchandize of
you:</hi> and in ver. 14. <hi>Having eyes full of Adultery, and that cannot
ceaſe from ſin, beguiling unſtable ſouls: an heart they have</hi> [Mark
what a one it is;] <hi>exerciſed with covetous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; curſed children
which have forſaken the right way, and are gone aſtray following the way
of</hi> Balaam <hi>the ſon of</hi> Boſor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This
<hi>Balaam</hi> is he that propheſied for gifts and rewards: See alſo
<hi>Iudes</hi> Epiſtle; and there mayſt thou ſee theſe Mercenary
Teachers limmed as it were in a Prophetical picture or Idea, when as yet they
were rather ſeen then felt. But to the query briefly thus I anſwer; If ye
be Miniſters of man, and not of Chriſt, its then conſentaneous, that from
man yee do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo procure a promiſe for maintenance, and not that ye rely on
God in this behalfe; ſeeing his promiſe and care hereabout reſpecteth
true Miniſters, and not ſuch as ye are. But be it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that ye
ſhould procure no ſuch promiſe for your main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance: Suppoſe all
forced maintenance were taken a way, Do you believe notwithſtanding, that God
and the people would adminiſter to you a competent maintenance? If you do
ſo believe, then what need of this indenting, and procuring of promiſe for
ſuch competent maintenance; together with your ſuits to the Magiſtrate
and others? (For none of theſe things did Chriſts Miniſters of old time
practice, and yet had they food and rayment even to contentment.) If you do not
believe it, but do doubt thereof, then do you clearly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that you
eſteem your ſelves to be leſſe regarded both of God and man, then
thoſe you count and call ſeducing Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Teachers of Hereſie,
Blaſphemy, &amp;c. for all ſuch, you ſee, have a competent maintenance,
and yet do they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver indent, or uſe other ſuch meanes to obtain it, as
you<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118999:17"/>do: Neither yet are they Murmerers and Complainers as
both the falſe Teachers in <hi>Jude</hi> 16. and moſt of you are, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
things pertaining to maintenance; VVill ye deny it? I appeal to the Court of
Exchequer (which yet is your grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt friend) I appeal to all the Pariſhes
(almoſt) in <hi>England,</hi> If ſuch ye be not. And for a concluſion of
this Anſwer, I do ſeriouſly commend unto you (ye indenting Covenanting
Preachers) the reading of <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. eſpecially the 15. <hi>verſ.
And</hi> [Judas] <hi>ſaid unto them,</hi> VVhat will ye give me? &amp;c.
<hi>and they Covenanted with him for thirty pieces of Silver.</hi> Is not here
your very type? Can any two things be more alike, than <hi>Judas</hi> and
<hi>you? What will ye gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e me</hi>
(ſaith he)? Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ye not this language? <hi>And they covenanted with
him, &amp;c.</hi> And is not this your 
<note n="*" place="margin">For Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting is a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or
reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> practiſe alſo? Not one Egg more like
another.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>38</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> VVhether the
Apoſtles did ever forbid all Suits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtians? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
6.1,2,3,4,5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the place here cited, it appeareth, That the
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reprehended, and that ſeverely, the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> for
going to Law before the unjuſt and unbeleevers; adviſing them in effect to
refer their Controverſies unto the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Saints and Chriſtian
Brethren. Now the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in thoſe times, as is well known, were not
Judges of Civil Courts, and ſo had not power to enforce the execution of
their Judgement (if at any time they had judged of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies) or
otherwiſe to puniſh the Contemners thereof. Had you alſo ſued in ſuch
manner, and with like event, we ſhould then have little to ſay againſt
you, touching this point. And yet here doth the Apoſtle allow no better
event, and fruit of ſuch Judgements, than is above implyed: For had he been
otherwiſe minded, I ſee no reaſon why he ſhould have ſo grievouſly
taxed theſe <hi>Corinthians.</hi> But how ſure a Patron the ſame
<hi>Paul</hi> is to your unreaſonable Suits at Law; If ye liſt to know,
read but the 9th <hi>verſe</hi> of the fore-quoted <hi>Chapter: N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w therefore there is utterly a fault
among ye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye go to Law one with another: Why do ye not rather take
wrong? Why do ye not rather ſuffer your ſelves to be defrauded?</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118999:18"/>Oh, how is this Scripture, ſo full of right Chriſtian
Spirit, by men of your Trade contemned! Do you never go to Law, but before the
Saints, as <hi>Paul</hi> here adviſeth? Do you never Sue before the unjuſt,
which <hi>Paul</hi> here diſſwadeth: Think ye it was ſutable to this mind
of <hi>Paul,</hi> to approve your many and coſtly Suits, with your trebble
Damages to boot; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially your title to the thing Demanded, and other
circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances being withal conſidered? Yea, rather with what indignation
and bitterneſs, would he have pronounced, <hi>There's utterly a fault
amongſt you?</hi> See more in the next Section.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>39</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> VVhether
Miniſters may not make uſe of one Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God for the upholding of
another, <hi>viz.</hi> Miniſters Maintenance? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You are firſt of all to prove that you are
that, whereof you deceitfully vaunt your ſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſts true
Miniſters: In the mean time you do but ſtrutt and ſwagger under a falſe
Name, like as ſometimes vile <hi>Scenicks</hi> do in a Princes robe and
Perſon. To your Query therefore I give this Anſwer; If Chriſts true
Miniſters ye be not, then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that your Miniſtery is not at all to
be upheld, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſt down. But if ye be ſuch; then again it is
evident, That never had theſe need (that I read, or know) to make uſe of
the Magiſtracy for their maintenance; at leaſt not ſuch a maintenance as
is here diſputed. To the Scripture cited in the Query, I Anſwer; That the
livelihood there meant, was the voluntary Contribution of Beleevers (as I have
ſhewed before) and no forced maintenance, (as you would have it.) But it's
apparent <hi>John Wickliffe</hi> (whom alſo I have formerly alleaged) was of
quite another mind and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than you are: For thus he ſaith,
[<hi>Art.</hi> 3. <hi>Complaint</hi>] <hi>Of which authority it is plain and
open, That the things that be due to</hi> Prieſts, <hi>ſhould not be</hi>
asked by Strength, by Violence, <hi>or</hi> by Curſing; <hi>but</hi> be given
freely without Exaction or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining. And a little after; <hi>Alſo
Chriſt with his Apoſtles lived moſt poor life as it is known by all the
proceſs of the Gospel, Nothing Challenging by Exaction, nor Conſtraining;
but lived <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118999:18"/>ſimply and ſcarcely enough of Alms freely and
wilfully given: Therefore they that pretend themſelves to be principal
Followers of Chriſts ſteps, ſhould live and walk as Chriſt did, and
ſo live full poor life, taking of things</hi> freely given, <hi>as much as
need is.</hi> Doubtleſs you think it foul ſcorn, and much beneath your
worth, to follow this wholeſome advice of <hi>Wickliffe,</hi> albeit it be
grounded on, and exactly conform both to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and Examples of
Chriſt, and all his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>40</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether a Child may
not run, when abuſed, for redreſs, to his Nurſing Father? <hi>Iſa.</hi>
49.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Think ye that the Magiſtrate, is there called
Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Father, becauſe of his feeding the Miniſters of Chriſt, or
others, with earthly food? And yet 'tis not long ſince, that ye called him
Dry Nurſe; namely, when he diverted from your mouths (then gaping wide to
receive it) his milk of Biſhops, and Dean and Chapters Lands.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>41</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether the Tenth
part of the Increaſe be not by the Law as due to Miniſters, as the Nine
parts remaining to the Poſſeſſor?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Your Right to the Tenth of the Increaſe of
Peoples Goods, is it not one and the ſame with the Right of the late
Monopoliſts, which they had to their Penſions out of Pins, Soap, &amp;c?
For this did they beg of the Magiſtrate; and by what other way do you come by
your Right to the Tenth of Increaſe? The People do buy their Lands, Sheep,
&amp;c. for money, at reaſonable Eſtimations; and that of the right and
private Owner: Do you in like manner acquire your Right to the Tenth of
Increaſe? The Title you get by Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, what is it elſe but a Beggarly
Right?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>42</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> VVhether
Miniſters, when all peaceable means; &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> VVhen ye ſhall have prov'd your ſelves to
have as good Propriety in Tithes, as other men have in their Eſtates, we
ſhall grant you then, That you may as juſtly appeal alſo to the
Chriſtian Magiſtrate, for the obtaining thereof, as any other man for the
procuring of his demands.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>43</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> VVhether your
decrying of trebble Damages, &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:118999:19"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's well for the falſe
Prophet, he hath the Beaſt to ride on: But tell us of that Magiſtrate that
gave you trebble Damages, or other Mulcts, that ye now can lawfully ſue for
in any Court that is extant? VVhat one Magiſtrate for you did, 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>i.e.</hi> Took away the
Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Courts; wherein alone it was lawful to ſue for
Tythes.</note>another hath undone; as I formerly noted.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>44</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether it be not
covetouſneſs, and no conſcience to refuſe to pay that, which is due,
and unjuſtly to detain that which is neither yours, nor was your Fathers by
Gift or Purchaſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If any man there be that ſo doth, far be it
from me to defend him. But what ſay ye to them, that bought <hi>All</hi>
their Cloſes, Grounds, Tenements, &amp;c. and this without all exception of
the Tith, or any other part? You'l ſay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, he did not buy the Tenth of
the Corn, Hay, &amp;c. <hi>Anſw.</hi> No more did he buy the ninth,
ſeventh, ſixth, or other part, <hi>viz.</hi> in words expreſs: Is it
lawful therupon for another to go to the Magiſtrate, &amp; beg all theſe
parts of the increaſe of my land; or could the Magiſtrate juſtifie ſuch
a Gift? Although it may ſeem in this matter, ye count all Fiſh that comes
to your Net. The Magiſtrate gives; <hi>Ergo,</hi> you may take, be it right
or wrong, you paſs not for that Which is language more befitting
Court-paraſites, and filching Monopoliſts, than ſuch as go under the name
(a great way you are beneath it) of Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>45</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether
<hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> Acts. 5.1,2. and thoſe mentioned
<hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8,9. had not as great reaſon to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Conſcience, as
thoſe that with-hold others due?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. When you alſo in like manner can avenge your
cauſe on them that with-hold your Tithes (ſo called) as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
there puniſh'd the ſin of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira;</hi> men will
lay the Tithes at your feet, and never ſtand out to a tryal with you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. We grant we are as well like <hi>Ananias</hi>
and <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira,</hi> as you are like <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. If our Caſe be the ſame with
<hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira's,</hi> your Right is then extended, not now
to the tenth, but or the whole price of our Poſſeſſions: and ſo we
ſhall be<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118999:19"/>but as your Alms-men, or Tenants by courteſie,
for the other Nine parts we keep.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>46</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> If by Petitioning
you mean the late Petition handed in this County; we ask, Whether that
abominable Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>Nayler,</hi> and his adherents, &amp;c?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It's notorious that thoſe your Petitions,
embraced a far greater number, than <hi>Nayler</hi> and his adherents, who were
not above ſix or ſeven (as I remember:) Yea, ſurely your Petitions were
as large (at leaſt in aime and vote) as <hi>Hamans</hi> Decree,
<hi>Eſther</hi> 3.13. namely, for deſtroying the whole Race of the Jews; as
before I have noted. And if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven they be blaſphemers, who <hi>ſay they are
Jews, and are not, Rev.</hi> 2.9. then are not they abominable blaſphemers,
who ſay they are Chriſts Miniſters and Embaſſadors, and are not, but
are rather ſo many Chieftains in <hi>the Synagogue of Satan?</hi> Yet did we
never Petition the Magiſtrate againſt you, nor wiſh you any evil; but
rather deſire that with perſecuting, and blaſphemous <hi>Saul,</hi> ye
may be converted, and your ſins for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given. So fulfilling the Commands of
Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that
hate you, pray for them that deſpightfully uſe you, and perſecute
you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>47</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether
Miniſters, or your Selves, occaſioned the Tumults and incivilities (if
there were any) at the time of your Meeting at <hi>Aiſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If there were any! Why, what plainner Tumult
could have been made; and what greater incivilities could have been committed,
than were at the Meeting at <hi>Aiſh?</hi> Thruſting, puſhing, pulling,
haling, renting of clothes; throwing of apples, dirt, ſticks: hooting,
ſhouting, loud laughters, ſcoffing, jearing, &amp;c. Do not, I ſay, all
theſe amount to a Tumult? Any one of theſe things in your Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings would
be counted occaſion enough for a tumult. And when did this ſavage uproar
begin? VVhen thoſe called Miniſters came to the Meeting. How, and with whom
did they come? They came with a multitude of rude Fellows, having Corn-pikes,
clubs, ſtaves, even in like manner, and with like company, and almoſt like
armed, as <hi>Judas</hi> their<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118999:20"/>elder brother, came againſt
Chriſt to betray him, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.14,15.47. But I hear the Relation it
ſelf is to be Printed; to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>48</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> VVhether your
uſual courſe of coming into our Aſſemblies, and railing at, and
reviling at Miniſters without the leaſt provocation, be not an occaſion
of Tumults?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was not railing, nor reviling, when the true
Prophets called the falſe Teachers, Preachers for hire; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viners for money;
Dumb dogs; Greedy dogs; Idol ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds; Ravening VVolves, and the like. And
what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is it of Tumults (in a Chriſtian; yea, in a civil, or
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Congregation) if theſe or the like names be now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo given,
to thoſe, to whom the ſame do no leſs truly belong; and that through the
movings and impulſe of the ſame holy Spirit, as led the ſaid Prophets to
do ſo before? But a very ſmall matter will put your Diſciples into a
tumult, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were in any good order: And a ſlight offence will them
provoke, who are the children of wrath, and have fingers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver itching to
ſhed bloud; the bloud of the innocent.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>49</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> He
<hi>quaeries,</hi> VVhether when the Scriptures ſpeak of the Saints being
Perfect, they be not to be meant of the laſt day?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Ye do prudently, Friends, to adjourn Perfection
unto the very laſt day; as being conſcious to your own ſelves, The VVomb
of your Miniſtry is too baſe and barren a thing, to bear and bring forth
ſo goodly fruit. But if the Saints may be perfect on the laſt day, why not
as well a day, a month, a year before? Your Caſe is even thus; You are
convinced by a many plain Scripture, That the Saints are per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect, (as anon I ſhall alſo prove)
Now becauſe the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of your School (with the Maſters and all) are at
ſo great diſtance from perfection (though they be ever learning, 2
<hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7.) They have invented this Artifice to ſalve the matter; No
man, ſay they, is perfect but when he's a dying, (as ſome) or till the
laſt day (as others ſay.) And now do they think they have got a ſure
ſhield, for to ward off all Aſſaults of them, who may charge them with
ſin, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection:<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118999:20"/>perfection: But this ſhield is
too narrow for their turn, as may appear by the Scriptures enſuing: 
<list>
                  <item>1 To be perfect is one of Gods Commandments,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48. And the Commandments of God are not grievous, 1
<hi>John</hi> 5:3: If not grievous, then not impoſſible; ſeeing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
that which is grievous, is yet poſſible to be done: And he that keeps Gods
Commandments (which may be done) the ſame is perfect.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Ye are my friends if ye do whatſoever I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mmand
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou,</hi> Joh. 15 14: The Saints are
Chriſts friends; and therefore do they whatſoever Chriſt commandeth them:
and they that ſo do are perfect.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>The Saints are Gods workmanſhip,</hi> Eph: 2:10:
<hi>But the workmanſhip of God perfect,</hi> Deut: 32:9:</item>
                  <item>4 <hi>He that neither ſinneth, nor can ſin, is perfect:
But ſuch are they that are born of God,</hi> 1 Joh: 3:9: 1 Joh: 5:18:</item>
                  <item>5 <hi>He</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>gave ſome Apoſtles, and
ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, &amp;c. for the perfecting of the
Saints,</hi> Eph: 4:12:13: Did not thoſe Apoſtles, Prophets, &amp;c. attain
the end for which they were given? Or elſe did their Miniſtery ſuſpend
its operation and effect until the laſt day?</item>
                  <item>6 It's poſſible for the Saints to come unto a perfect
man; to the meaſure of the ſtature of Chriſts fulneſs, <hi>Eph:</hi>
4:13,14: And they that be here, be ſurely perfect. Now that theſe things
are all attainable in this life; and that alſo many years before the hour of
death, is evident by what is immediately ſubjoyned, <hi>viz. That we
henceforth be no more Children toſſed to and fro, and carried about with
every wind of Doctrine by the ſlight of men, &amp;c.</hi> It's ſaid
<hi>[that henceforth]</hi> that is, From the time of their being a perfect man
and of being come to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of Chriſts fulneſs;
elſe, will the ſenſe be broken, jarring, and altogether incoherent. And
ſurely all thoſe things that follow <hi>[Henceforth]</hi> do imply a much
larger time, than the <hi>laſt day.</hi> Had <hi>Paul</hi> here been of the
<hi>Querents</hi> mind, That perfection comes not till the <hi>laſt day,</hi>
would he have ſaid, <hi>That henceforth;</hi> that is, That after the Saints
be perfect, and be come to the meaſure of Chriſts ſtature, <hi>They 
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118999:21"/>be no more children toſſed too and fro &amp;c. For what
ſpace, time, or danger or poſſibility, could he then have conceived, of
their being toſſed too and fro with every winde of Doctrine &amp;c.</hi>
This is, after the laſt day: on which day the querents ſuppoſes that the
Saints are to be made perfect; and not before.</item>
                  <item>7. If any man offend not in word, the ſame is a perfect
man <hi>Iam:</hi> 3:2: Now it's impoſſible that there ſhould be ſuch
men, as <hi>Iames</hi> here deſcribeth. Or did he here only propoſe the
Idaea or Patern of a perfect man, which never yet had, nor never was to have
actuall being? This were rather to make him a Platonick Philoſopher, then one
of Chriſts faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſters: and a nugatory ſpeculator rather, then a
teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of things to be done.</item>
                  <item>8. Now the God of peace—make you perfect in good
works to do his will <hi>Heb:</hi> 13:20:21: If we be not made perfect till the
laſt day, what ſpace of time then remaineth, wherein, after one is perfect,
he may do the will of God. Think ye that this prayer regardeth only the laſt
day? Was it needful to pray that believers might be made perfect in good works
to do Gods will on the laſt day? Would you not have Gods will to be done
before that day? See 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 13.1. Finally brethren farewell; be
perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace <hi>&amp;c:</hi> Are
all theſe things not attainable before the laſt day? Or are ſome before;
and ſome (or one) not till then?</item>
                  <item>9: Mark the perfect man, behold the upright, for the end of
that man is peace <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 37:37. Do theſe words ſo ſound as if
<hi>David</hi> held no man perfect untill the laſt day? Is not the peaceable
end, here ſpoken of, the effect or conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant of perfection? But if no man
be perfect till the laſt day what ſenſe can be gathered from theſe
words? What end is the perfect man to have at, or after the laſt day? And who
is then to mark it?</item>
                  <item>10. <hi>Heb:</hi> 7.19: For the Law made nothing perfect,
but the bringing in of a better hope did <hi>&amp;c:</hi> He doth not ſay
ſhall; &amp; that at the laſt day: Again <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. For by one
offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified. They 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118999:21"/>therefore that are ſanctified, are likewiſe Perfected:
But men are ſanctified before the laſt day. 
<p>Alſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22.23. But ye are come unto Mount
<hi>Sion &amp;c.</hi> and to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now how could the Saints be then come to the ſpirits of
juſt men made perfect, If it be true, that none be made perfect till the
laſt day.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>11. Let us therefore as many as be Prefect be thus minded
<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. Now if neither <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, nor any other
were at this time perfect, this exhortation were void of all ſenſe and
reaſon: For if none were then perfect whom did he then exhort?</item>
                  <item>12. Howbeit we ſpeak Wiſdom among them that are
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. Now if none can be perfect till the laſt day,
then will it neceſſarily follow, that either <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake
Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom among them that were not perfect, or elſe among none at all. But
both theſe are falſe. 
<p>Objection: <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe profeſſes that he
was not made perfect <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.12.13. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The perfection
there ſpoken of, is to be underſtood of a certain degree or meaſure of
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which <hi>Paul</hi> at that time had not attained unto; and not of
perfection, ſimply conſidered: Otherwiſe this place ſhould contradict
other both many &amp; evident Scriptures; yet doth the ſame <hi>Paul</hi>
ſay in the following words: But I follow after if that I may apprehend that
for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> alſo I am apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Chriſt: and in <hi>Verſ</hi> 14. He
ſaith, I preſſe toward the mark <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now did he follow after,
and preſſe towards this degree of perfection in faith, or not in faith? If
in faith, then did he believe it poſſible to be attained unto. See more of
this point hereafter.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item>13. Finally, the Scriptures give this teſtimony of
<hi>Noah, Job,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> that they were perfect men,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Job</hi> 1.8. and this was long time ago.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>50</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether can you
rationally expect that our hearers ſhould be more perfect then the eleven
Apoſtles. [<hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant indeed 'twere very abſurd to expect
your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers ſhould be perfect while they are under ſuch imperfect 
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118999:22"/>Teachers.] <hi>Thoſe ſtars of the higheſt magnitude
in the Church.</hi> [<hi>Anſw.</hi> And yet the Prieſts, Scribes, and
Phariſees could not abide them, but ſought to pluck them out of their
Firmament.] <hi>Whom yet Chriſt upbraideth with unbelief and hardneſſe of
heart.</hi> [<hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a childhood in grace, they had not as
yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Promiſe of the Father, which was the gift of the Spirit;
neither were their underſtandings yet opened, &amp;c. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15 26.
&amp; 20.22. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24 45,49. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1,2,3,4.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>51</label>
               <hi>Ob. Eccleſ.</hi> 7.20.
<hi>James</hi> 3.2. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. Anſw. I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but he that is
a Saint may commit ſin; but ye the that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in Chriſt ſinneth not:
<hi>Reſiſt the Devil and he will flye;</hi> Here <hi>I</hi> demand whether
it be poſſible to reſiſt the devil and all other temptations to ſin?
If thou ſay it's poſſible at all times ſo to reſiſt; then it
follows, That a Saint may forbear at all times from ſinning, and ſo never
ſin: But if thou ſay its impoſſible ſo to reſiſt, and that he
muſt needs give way to temptations, and ſo commit ſin, Then is this not
to be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſin which thus is not willingly committed, but as an
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced paſſion, and is of the ſame accompt with a Rape, which a woman
may ſuffer without any guilt of ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>52</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether, though
none of our Hearers in this life either are, or can be free from the reliques
and remainders of ſin, <hi>Ro.</hi> 7.23,24. yet whether many of them are not
perfectly freed from the condemnation of ſin, <hi>Rom</hi> 8:1: &amp; 33,34.
yea, &amp; ſo far from the dominion and power of ſin, <hi>Rom:</hi> 6:14:
that though ſin be in them, yet they are not in ſin? but that we may
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably believe that teſtimony of them which the Scripture gives of
<hi>Iob, Iob</hi> 1:1. That they feare God and eſchew evil? And that
notwithſtanding their human frailties and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yet nevertheleſſe
their hearts, as the heart of <hi>Aſa</hi> was, are perfect all their dayes,
2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. ſo perfect as to be ſincere and upright?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Concerning the righteouſneſſe and
perfection of your Hearers; I <hi>Anſwer:</hi> That by their fruits they are
known. And if they be not free from ſin, then not dead to ſin; and ſo
under the Law and not under grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6: <hi>Rom.</hi>
6:18:22:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:118999:22"/>In <hi>Rom.</hi> 3:23,24: <hi>Paul</hi>
declareth his warring eſtate, at which time he was <hi>carnal, ſold under
ſin,</hi> verſe 14: <hi>brought into the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity to the law of
ſin,</hi> verſe 23: At which time he alſo cryeth out, <hi>Oh wretched man
that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death!</hi> But the
ſame <hi>Paul</hi> in other places doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a far different eſtate
from this: for thus he ſaith, <hi>When we were in the fleſh,</hi> verſe
5: <hi>Ye are not in the fleſh,</hi> Rom. 8.9. <hi>For the law of the
ſpirit of life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made me free from the law of ſin
and death,</hi> Rom. 8:2: <hi>How can we that are dead to ſin, live any
longer therein?</hi> Rom.<hi>And if Chriſt be in you the body is dead
becauſe of ſin,</hi> Rom. 8.10. See alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. From theſe,
and many other places that might have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged, it is moſt evident,
That <hi>Paul</hi> in this ſeventh Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> treateth
of his warfare, &amp; of the condition he then was in while yet he was not
wholly dead to ſin, nor had yet obtained the victory over the carnal part;
and ſo was not yet delivered from under the thunders and tempeſt of
<hi>Sinai's</hi> condemnation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>53</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether any of you
received the myſtery of Chriſt by Revelation, the ſame way that
<hi>Paul</hi> did, who received it by Chriſts ſpeaking to him in the Hebrew
tongue: compare <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.3,4,5. with <hi>Acts</hi> 26.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſeemeth to me a very ſilly
<hi>quaere;</hi> as though the language in which God ſpeaketh, when he calls
any one to the Miniſtery, or other ſervice, were of any conſideration or
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as in reſpect to the validity of ſuch a Call, and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
thereby received: Let the Reader compare theſe two Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturers (in the
<hi>quaere</hi>) and he ſhall find the latter end of this queſtion yet
worſe than the beginning.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>54</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether thoſe
faithful men at <hi>Epheſus</hi> to whom <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> committed thoſe
things that he had heard of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 22. and 3.14. And
whether thoſe Elders that were ordained in <hi>Creet,</hi> by <hi>Titus,</hi>
whom <hi>Paul</hi> left there for that purpoſe, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. might not
be truly ſtiled Miniſters made by Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> by
Chriſts appointment; though they were not Apoſtles, Prophets, or
Evangeliſts?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:118999:23"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To that of
<hi>Timothy,</hi> I Anſwer; 1. They were to be faithful men. 2. It follows
not, That this committing of things heard, &amp;c unto them, did make and
conſtitute ſuch men <hi>ipſo facto</hi> Chriſts Miniſters. 3.
<hi>Timothy</hi> was able to judge who were fit and able, <hi>To teach others
alſo.</hi> Did ſuch a man, or men, as <hi>Timothy</hi> was, give any of you
commiſſion to teach others? Of this before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Neither doubt I but <hi>Titus</hi> had good
Authority to Ordain thoſe Elders, (ſo as the place importeth.) And had your
Ordainers as good alſo, I ſhould as little doubt theirs too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. If your Ordainers had Ordained ſuch
Miniſters as <hi>Paul</hi> there deſcribeth, and appoints to be Ordained,
<hi>Tit.</hi> 1.6,7,8,9,10. I believe I ſhould readily own and embrace them:
For ſuch had been <hi>blameleſs, ſober, juſt, holy, temperate,</hi> and
not given to <hi>Filthy Lucre, &amp;c.</hi> which are ſuch vertues and graces
we cannot yet ſee in any of you, no, not though we ſtand never ſo near
you: Whereas the contrary vices are ſo vigorous in you, that you yield a bad
ſcent wherever you come; with them that have ſenſes incorrupt, to
<hi>ſmell it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 4: And is it not rather to be ſaid, That this
ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Elders was not a conſtituting of Miniſters ſimply; but an
aſſigning or appointing of them, that were ſuch before, to ſome new,
and ſpecial, or particular charge, or ſervice? The word is as well, if not
better engliſhed, <hi>Settle, Place:</hi> Alſo this ſence, the cohering
words do favour; <hi>In every City;</hi> He ſaith not <hi>of ſuch or ſuch
a place, or Church;</hi> nor yet <hi>Elders</hi> ſimply.</p>
            <p>Finally, It's here to be remembred what kind of Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was in
uſe in thoſe Primitive times; For this ſee <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>55</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether Chriſts
promiſe, That he would be with his Apoſtles unto the end of the World,
<hi>Matth</hi> 28.19,20. can be any otherwiſe made good then in his being
preſent with ordinary Paſtors, that ſhould ſucceed in the Church to the
end of the world?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the place be ſo to be underſtood as the
<hi>Quaerent</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:118999:23"/>taketh it, then where were thoſe
Paſtors and Succeſſors to the Apoſtles; and how was God with them for
ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds or years, even during all the time of Popiſh Apoſtacy,
which began even in the Apoſtles age? But your main buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is, to
prove your ſelves to be true Paſtors of Chriſt; which ye never can do,
ſo long as ye continue Hirelings (See <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.12.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>56</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether ordinary
Paſtors and Teachers are not as well ſaid to be given for the Work of the
Miniſtry &amp;c as well as Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, <hi>Eph</hi>
4 11,12. and that till we all come to the meaſure of the ſtature of the
fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. which is not, cannot be till the
end of the world; compare <hi>Epheſ</hi> 4.11,12,13. with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
12.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 I deny your diſtinction of Paſtors into
<hi>ordinary</hi> and <hi>extraordinary</hi> (taking the word Paſtor as
diſtinct from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, &amp;c) This is your caſe; ye are aſham'd to
claim to your ſelves the name of Apoſtle or Paſtor in a Scripture
ſenſe, which you ſeem to call <hi>extraordinary;</hi> This <hi>one</hi>
name therefore ye craftily divide into <hi>two;</hi> that being driven from the
poſſeſſion of the one (i. e. <hi>exttaordinary</hi>) ye may yet as a
reſerve, have the other to flye to: imitating herein (after a ſort) thoſe
Spirits, that being commanded to go out of the man, prayed they might have
leave to paſs into the Swine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Ye cannot away to hear of the Saints arrival
to the meaſure of Chriſts ſtature: Why? Becauſe ye your ſelves are
ſo ſhort thereof: Alſo well know ye in your ſelves, That as many as are
come hither, or fair in the way thereto, be now tall enough to over-look all
your deceits and failings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 3. I demand, Whether All the Saints ſhall come
to this neaſure all at one time; that is, (as you ſay) at the end of the
world? If ye ſay, Yea; then it ſeems (after your ſenſe) the Saints
ſhall neither till then come to the unity of the Faith, or the knowledge of
the Son of God: Foraſmuch as both theſe are coupled together with the
other; which were very abſurd to affirm, (taking the <hi>end of the
world</hi> in that ſenſe you take it) and openly contradictory to many
other places of Scriptures. Whoſoever is truly in the Faith; is one with 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118999:24"/>all others who are likewiſe in the ſame Faith. The
Beleevers of old time were all of one heart, and of one ſoul (<hi>Acts</hi>
4.32) were not theſe come to the Unity of the Faith; &amp; alſo in the way
of attaining to the meaſure of Chriſts ſtature, &amp;c.? The one Faith
being in many, makes them all of one heart, mind, and conſent: We are one
bread; fellow-members of the ſame body. See alſo, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7.
Again, how can a man be a true Believer, that is not, in ſome meaſure, come
to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Son of God? See <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
2.2. <hi>Phil</hi> 3.10 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.3. &amp;
2.13, &amp;c. Now that all theſe things, namely, Unity of the Faith;
Knowledge of the Son of God, and Coming to be a Perfect man, are referred to
one and the ſame time, (<hi>i e.</hi> the time of this life) with coming to
the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of Chriſts fulneſs, is very plain, in that
they are all alike joyned together in one form, and manner of ſpeech under
the word <hi>[until.]</hi> See more of this in <hi>Section</hi> 49:6.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>57</label>
               <hi>T L.</hi> Whether
Magiſtrates are not truly ſtyled Miniſters of God, though ordained by
men?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw</hi> Magiſtrates indeed are Gods very Miniſters,
but in Civil, not in a Spiritual accompt: And yet if the Magiſtrate, ſo
well as ye now account him, ſhould once abandon your <hi>Function</hi> to
voluntary Contribution, you would turne your Tale, I beleeve:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>58</label>
               <hi>T:L.</hi> Whether thoſe
that ſay none other things than thoſe which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the
Prophets did ſay ſhould come, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.22. and that determine to
know nothing; yea, to Preach nothing but Jeſus Chriſt and him Crucified,
and that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures, may not be rightly ſtyled to ſpeak
as the Oracles of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They only are to be ſaid to ſpeak as the
Oracles of God, who ſpeak by inſpiration or revelation of the holy Ghoſt;
or elſe in the Light ſpeak thoſe things which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have handled
and taſted, both ſeaſonably and aptly for the edification, or benefit of
the hearers: But they that are in the fleſh cannot pleaſe God,
(<hi>Rom.</hi> 8 8.) whatever they ſay, or determine to know, or preach. And
though ye may<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118999:24"/>uſe the words of Scripture, yet cannot ye
thus be covered: the Tempter ſo did, and that cunningly too; and yet got he
thereby no thank at all at Chriſts hands: No more do you neither by Preaching
long Sermons compiled of words ſtoln in like manner out of the Scriptures,
(and other Books)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> That theſe are very vertues, &amp;c. And yet we
affirm, That, through Grace, ſome; yea, many of us, have attained to this,
That even the piercing <hi>eye of malice</hi> it ſelf cannot ſee ſo far
as juſtly to charge us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>eye of wiſdome</hi> then ſees farthet
than the <hi>eye of malice;</hi> for this ſees you full of iniquities: Now
the <hi>eye of malice</hi> is of your ſide, and therefore not ſo apt to
charge you, how far ſoever it may ſee into your guiltineſs; yea even this
<hi>piercing eye</hi> hath a <hi>mote</hi> in it ſelf, and therefore cannot
ſee a <hi>beam</hi> in yours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> That our Gifts and Converſations are not, at
leaſt, in a competent meaſure, ſuitable to that high Calling, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
we are called; However not unto us, not unto us, [you mean not here of Tythes,
and Augmentations, &amp;c.] but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our God's name be the praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Our Gifts</hi> — If ye were indeed
<hi>wiſe,</hi> yet your <hi>Gifts</hi> would blind your eyes: Your
<hi>Converſations,</hi> they are like a <hi>menſtruous garment,</hi>
whereof is no part remaining clean, but is wholly defiled Your <hi>Calling</hi>
is from the <hi>Serpent,</hi> and your <hi>Gifts</hi> and
<hi>Converſations</hi> are ſuitable to it. But why is your <hi>Calling</hi>
an high <hi>Calling;</hi> Becauſe it ſets you in the Pulpit on high? It's
certain, were it not for Tythes and rich Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, the moſt of your number
would turn the deaf ear to this <hi>High Calling,</hi> and ſay they never
heard ſound thereof. But how bountiful ye are to God! <hi>To his Name be the
praiſe.</hi> A few empty words without any true ground. Go, offer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God
the <hi>firſtlings of your flock, and the fat thereof;</hi> until ye ſo do,
the Lord will have no more reſpect to your Sacrifice, than he had unto his,
who for envy ſlew his Brother; (a vice moſt truly yours)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>60</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether when the
Obedience and ſatisfaction of Chriſt, our Surety, unto the Law and
Juſtice of God, is by<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118999:25"/>God the Father freely imputed to us,
the righteouſneſs of the Law may not in the Apoſtles ſenſe
(<hi>Rom</hi> 8.4.) be truly ſaid to be fulfilled in us, or by us, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5 19,21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here may the Reader take a taſte whereby to
judge what kind of Interpreters ye are of the Scriptures; the which where they
fit, not your purpoſe, or fanſie, ye ſtick not to wreſt, contract,
extend, at the beck of each frivolous Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, juſt as if they were a Noſe
of VVax But <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declared what he means, when he
ſaith, <hi>That the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of the law might be fulfilled in
us</hi> [not <hi>out of us,</hi>] in that he adds immediately after, <hi>Who
walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit;</hi> And they that ſo walk,
do verily fulfil the righteouſneſs of the Law. By theſe words therefore
he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the mean, or way, wherein, or whereby ſuch
righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is fulfilled</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>61</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> VVhether thoſe
that are ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. to ſpeak by immediate revelation were
not extraordinary Officers, and ſuch as continued only for a time in the
Church of God and its firſt planting, and are now ceaſed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> VVhile the Churches did abide in the Truth and
wayes of God, ſo long was God alſo with them; and they did feel the movings
of his Spirit, and ſpake accordingly as of it they were moved: But when they
began to forſake their firſt love, and to joyn with the whore and falſe
Prophets, and to worſhip the Beaſt, then did God alſo juſtly with-draw
himſelf from them; then did their Sun begin to ſet, and the ſhadows of
Night enſued. Now heard they not the VVord of the Lord, nor the workings of
his Spirit did they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, but became eſtranged thereunto. In theſe
dayes did they make a Calf, and offered ſacrifice to the Idol, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced
in the works of their own hands</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>62</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> VVhether thoſe
extraordinary Officers were not ſtyled Prophets, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4 11. 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though all in the Primitive Churches were not
Prophets, yet was it lawful in thoſe true Churches (though forbidden in
yours) for any man to Propheſie, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or reſtraint: For thus
ſaith <hi>Paul, Ye may all propheſie<pb n="45" facs="tcp:118999:25"/>one by one</hi> 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31. and in Verſ 1. he ſaith, <hi>Follow after Charity and
deſire ſpirituall gifts,</hi> but rather that ye may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy: Alſo
Verſ. 5. <hi>I would that ye ſpake with tongues, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ye
propheſy.</hi> Hence it is manifeſt that <hi>Paul</hi> permitted any one to
propheſy: and not only ſo, but ſecondly, alſo exhorteth them all
indifferently to deſire the gift of propheſy (not the office:) And,
thirdly, He declares his willingneſs that they 
<note n="*" place="margin">Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be of the ſame
mind with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> who deſired that all the Lords people were
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</note> all might propheſy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now in Verſ 3. he
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth what he meaneth by propheſying, namely, <hi>A ſpeaking unto men
to edification exhortation and comfort;</hi> and this by revelation of the
ſpirit; as may be gathered of Verſ. 30 Let us now erect a compariſon,
between the ſpeaking and order that were in the Churches of Chriſt of old
time, and the ſpeaking and order (ſuch as it is) that are in your meetings
at this day. 1. In thoſe it was lawful, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to order, for All to
ſpeak: In yours only for One to ſpeak. 2. In thoſe they did ſpeak by
revelation of God: In yours they ſpeak by imagination of their own brain. 3.
In thoſe they did ſpeak for edification, exhortation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of
others: In yours for Augmentation, Decimation, and benefit of themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>63</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether when the
Apoſtle ſaith that all may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy, he doth yet ſuffer a woman to
ſpeak in the Church <hi>&amp;c</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Ioel</hi> (<hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>Verſ</hi> 28)
propheſyed, that (not their ſons only, but alſo) their daughters ſhould
propheſy <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where? To whom? Doth not propheſying ſerve for
them which believe? (1. <hi>Cor:</hi> 14 22) And if to one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, ſuch
propheteſſes might rightly propheſy; why not alſo to two, to three, or
more? If in a place where theſe beleivers did or do not uſually meet; why
not likewiſe in a-place where they uſually meet? If out of a houſe; why
not as well in a houſe? To a Church in a houſe? <hi>Philemon,</hi> 2 Or
ſay ye that the number and place do make and give being to the Church of God?
Define unto us then, how many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be neceſſarily required to the
making up of a Church? and alſo what place it behoveth to be, that with
ſuch number<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118999:26"/>muſt concur, to the ſo making up of a
Church</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>64</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether he doth
not alſo exclude private members from intruding on that great office of
propheſying when he demands, Are all Teachers <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What private members doth <hi>Paul</hi> exclude
from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying, when ſpeaking to the Church he ſaith, Ye may all
propheſy (1. <hi>Cor</hi> 14 31) Neither doth he only permitt (or rather
declare it to be lawfull) that all may propheſy; but deſireth alſo that
they all might have the gift of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy (Verſ. 5.) And finally exhorteth
the whole Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinctly that they deſire the gift of propheſy; as
is noted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Agreeable to this mind of <hi>Paul</hi> was alſo that of
<hi>Moſes;</hi> I would (ſaith he) <hi>that all the Lords people were
Prophets, and that the Lord would put his ſpirit upon them, Numb.</hi> 11.29.
Where alſo it is to be noted, that though <hi>Eldad</hi> and <hi>Medad</hi>
had never been counted or acknowledg'd as Prophets, but were private members of
the Iewiſh Church, yet did they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy, and that in the Camp; not
waiting for the triall or approbation of man, nor for any Solmn Inveſtiture
into the office of Prophets: It was ſufficient authority to them, to
propheſy, that the ſpirit of the Lord reſted upon them (Verſ. 26.) Now
<hi>Moſes</hi> when he heard thereof (yet not yet by what warrant they
propheſied) what did he do? Verily he ſet not the rude multitude upon them
to beat them, pull them, tear them, neither charged he the civil Officers to
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them, and carry them away for endleſſe Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: None of
theſe things (I ſay) did <hi>Moſes; But ſaith he, Envieſt thou for my
ſake? would God that all the Lords people were prophets &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Its plain therefore neither <hi>Paul</hi> nor <hi>Moſes</hi> to
have been of your Teachers mind, (to forbid any to propheſy;) but as far
diſtant from you herein (as in moſt other matters alſo) as namely becomes
the true ſervants of God, with Satans Miniſters compared.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>65</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> How can they
<hi>i. e.</hi> how can they lawfully and as to God acceptably preach, except
they be ſent? <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Apply this place unto your ſelves. Ye Preach for
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118999:26"/>hire, and Divine for money: ye are not the men that bring
glad tidings: [who deny men may be perfect and free from ſin in this life;]
that publiſh peace: [who bring along with ye the black Threats of war, and
manifold miſeries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that will not put into your mouthes] Neither
do ye publiſh ſalvation, [but keep men ever learning, that never come to
the knowledge of the truth, and the end of faith.] Underſtandeth not the
Apoſtle in this place ſuch a Sending as his alſo was? who was not ſent
of men, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by men, but by Jeſus Chriſt. And though the operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of
the ſpirit be divers, yet do they not all alike proceed from the ſpirit?
Did not the ſame ſpirit that made heretofore Apoſtles, make Paſtors
alſo? And dare you that call your ſelves Paſtors of Churches, pretend to
have received ſuch office and quality immediately of the ſpirit? I have
ſeldome known any of you ſo impudent. Wherefore your operation is not by
the ſame God; neither is your gift by the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, neither your
Adminiſtration by the ſame Lord Jeſus, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.5 6. And if
no man can ſay, that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt: How then
do you talk whole hours of Jeſus, without the Holy Ghoſt? But if ye yet
challenge to have the Holy Ghoſt, then make it to appeare, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
fruits thereof; ſuch are love, joy, peace, long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,
gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, faith, meekneſſe, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance; are theſe
things in you, or ſo much as the very ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, or counterfits thereof?
rather, bring you not forth ſuch fruits as be clean contrary to theſe? Let
the ſpiritual man be judge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>66</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether it be not
uſuall in our Churches to give liberty to ſeverall Miniſters, to
exerciſe their gifts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their office ſucceſſively one by
one decentlie and in order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Ye ſeem to have propounded this your practice
and order, as having ſome reſemblance and agreement with the practiſe and
order which <hi>Paul</hi> did adviſe to be obſerved in the Church at
<hi>Cornith:</hi> But even in this point do ye greatly differ and ſwerve from
the right patern, and fouly miſſe of<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118999:27"/>your mark: For 1.
The men that you ſuffer to preach in your meeting houſes, they be ſuch as
are known to have been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained or approved for this office of preaching, by
man. 2. Such Preachers, are Paſtors or Miniſters (falſly ſo called) of
ſeveral Churches (ſo named) and not of one: 3. They firſt have the leaves
of the Teacher of that Pariſh, where they are to preach. 4. They bring along
their Sermons with them ready prepared; and ſo do but reherſe what before
they had invented and compoſed. Now all theſe things, to omitt many other,
were quite otherwiſe in the Churches of Chriſt of old time, where due order
was obſerved. Will ye give liberty of ſpeech, or propheſying to any one
in your Aſſemblies, that is not made Miniſter by, or according to man?
That ſpeaketh forth that which God revealeth unto him? No; you appropriate
the uſe of ſpeaking, as it were a Monopoly, to your ſelves alone you may
ſpeak what you will, none may controule you, without danger of great harme
and impriſonment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>67</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether to be
hated for this very cauſe, becauſe we profeſſe our ſelves Miniſters
of the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We do not hate you becauſe you do profeſs your
ſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel; nor yet at all: Although we do not doubt
but ye are hated of the Lord, for this your Blaſphemy, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi>
2.9. Ye do indeed profeſs your ſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſpel,
but oh how ſhort do ye come of approving your ſelves as ſuch, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4.5.6 7.8.9.10 Where's your much patience? [while ye cannot
endure to hear a man ſpeak in your Aſſemblies, though moved of the Lord
thereunto:] Where your afflictions? [who cruelly vex, and perſecute others,
even the Saints of the moſt high, doing you no harme at all] where your
neceſſities and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſses? [who live at eaſe in the fleſh,
fareing dilitiouſly every day, and vie with the great men of the world, in
gay apparel and ſumptuous buildings:] where your ſtripes and
impriſonment? [do you not cauſe both theſe almoſt every week, to be
infflicted on others, even the Innocent?] where the tumults ye ſuſtain;
labours, watchings faſtings: where<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118999:27"/>the pureneſs,
knowledge, long-ſuffering, kindneſs, Holy Ghoſt, love unfeigned, &amp;c.
Do you not both cauſe others to ſuffer the former, and of the later are not
ye wholly voyd? Now then is it any way likely, or conſentaneous to any
ſound reaſon, that ye who call your ſelves Miniſters of the Goſpel,
and Succeſſors to <hi>Paul</hi> in this office, be ſuch as yee avouch
your ſelves to be? ſeeing not onely none of the things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid which
<hi>Paul</hi> ſuſtained ye likewiſe ſuffer, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by your
means and malice ye do even cauſe the ſame things to be ſuffred of
others, and that moſt wrongfully. Bluſh then and be aſhamed any longer to
arrogate to your ſelves this name, when as ye do ſuffer none of all thoſe
things that alwayes did accompany the ſame where it was truly owned.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>68</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether our calling
to the Miniſtery be not that which doth provoke your ſpleen and
bitterneſs againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Your calling to the Miniſtery doth no whit
provoke us, but your hypocriſie, but your deceit, your covetouſneſs,
pride, gluttony, luxury, crueltie, and the reſt of your vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Yet do not
theſe neither ſo provoke us, as at any time to pull you, hale you, ſtock
you, ſtone you, impriſon you, rifle your goods, &amp;c. Neither ever did we
ſo much as deſire that anie of theſe things might be done unto you, at
leaſt not ſince the time we were called <hi>Quakers,</hi> our witneſs is
on high.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> T.L. Whether many ſcores, and hundreds of
Miniſters of the Goſpel (ſuch as are we) have not laid down their lives
in the very flames for living godly in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> What ſtout Martyrs your brethren have been in
times of perſecution, is ſufficiently known to all Engliſh men whoſe
ages do number fortie yeers or upwards; for in ſuch mens remembrance, for
fear of the Biſhops Apparitors, or other ſmall trouble impending, they
ſhipped themſelves by ſcores for another land as is alſo before touched
But theſe things not ſo willingly do I remember, as well knowing that they
who ſo fled away were of the verie beſt of your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:118999:28"/>Thoſe you call Miniſters of the Goſpel
in the <hi>Quaerie,</hi> were not ſuch as ye are, ſave in name of Religion
and certain Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets; but were (at leaſt in ſpirit and frame of minde) as
far unlike you, as you are like them who ſo made them lay down their lives in
the very <hi>Flames</hi> (as the <hi>Quaere</hi> hath it.) Do not you
likewiſe perſecute men for living godly in Chriſt Jeſus, as theſe
alſo did? Bluſh to deny it. Do not you and your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples yet far
out-ſtrip in wrong and barbarous cruelty, all the generations of
perſecutors that ever were of old time? Thoſe executed their malice (for
the moſt part) by Proceſs at Law, with ſhew of Order and Civility; You or
your lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (with your well liking at leaſt) doubt not to commit all
manner of harm and ſavage crueltie not only without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie legall Proceſs,
but without any Law it ſelf; yea, clean contrary to 
<note n="†" place="margin">The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of
Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>Law. You make them to ſuffer, by whom part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you reign:
You make them poor, by whoſe means you are rich: You caſt them in priſon,
by whoſe bonds and travels you injoy your liberty. I ſay theſe things
have ye done partly in vote, and partly in fact, as is well known.</p>
            <p>Tell us now ye that are yet alive, or ye that have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
us, if ever like unkindneſs to this, ye have ſeen with your eyes, or heard
by report of others?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>70</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> VVhether you
durſt appeal to the Tribunal of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who are perſecutors in heart,
word, deed; you or wee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> O ſingular impudence! O boldneſs not to be
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched! Provokeſt thou us to heavens Tribunal for tryall of ſuch a
queſtion, as almoſt all (both men, women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) on earth can judge
and determine, and that without danger of erring? Does not almoſt everie
citie, town and village in the Nation ring and reſound of ſcoffs, taunts,
clamors againſt them that be called <hi>Quakers?</hi> Is there ever a
Priſon in <hi>England</hi> in the which are not ſome of our friends
detained? VVhat Judge is there? VVhat Juſtice that hath not had an hand in
condemning of our friends to ſome kind of puniſhment? Many other things I
here might recount, but I am even grown weary to mention them: And now to 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118999:28"/>bring the matter home to your own doors; Is there anie one
grievance or injurie that our friends do ſuffer, but it point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto you as
the cauſe thereof, and is to be charged on your account? And this may you not
your ſelves deny, while ye dare not but confeſs of your manie and infinite
accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, informations, ſubornations, teſtifications, abominations,
countenancings, and abettings, &amp;c. whereby all theſe wrongs and
afflictions have befallen our friends: And if there be haplie any ſuch among
you ſo far diſſenting from the reſt of their brethren, that have not
yet ſtained them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the guilt of any the things above remembred;
yet likely it is that even theſe alſo have tacitely and in heart
aſſented thereto, and approved the ſame: Or if there bee, who are even
hitherto clear, yet I challenge you all to this, <hi>viz.</hi> To name me the
man amongſt ye, that <hi>openly</hi> and of his <hi>own accord,</hi> hath
rebuked and earneſtly teſtified againſt thoſe many open ſins and
abuſes which their Hearers daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit on thoſe that are called
<hi>Quakers:</hi> Or that hath ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and diſpoſed them afore hand
by ſound teaching, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie inſtruction, and example of innocent life, that
they be not now apt to commit or intend ſuch violence and fury? But why
appeal ye to <hi>Heaven?</hi> Is it hence, becauſe that ye fear to refer your
cauſe to the judgement of anie here on earth? But whatever it be, if ye ſo
will appeal, I aſſure ye we dare to join with you herein; provided ye will
interpoſe good <hi>Caution</hi> to meet us there: for this of your part do we
verie much doubt, except ye mend your lives while ye be here on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> But to what end haſt thou mentioned the
<hi>Marian</hi> dayes in the following Quere? You are not much liker thoſe
Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in ſpirit and temper of mind (though you ſucceed them in name of
religion and certain opinions) then the <hi>Popes</hi> are like
<hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe Succeſſors they likewiſe pretend to be.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>72</label> What godly men do we call
<hi>Vipers, Serpents, children of the Devll, falſe deceivers?</hi> even
ſuch perſons, as holy men have formerly branded with the ſelf-ſame
names: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118999:29"/>ought you neither to call us Raylers
for ſo uſeing theſe names; unleſſe you can prove that theſe alſo
who ſo have done before us, were Railers too.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>73</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> To run up and down
ſtarke naked, as one of your Brethren at <hi>Exeter,</hi> and one of your
Siſters at <hi>Westminiſter &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I know not of any of our friends that ſo have
done, as here is ſurmiſed: As for one of them, I am ſure he was
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own'd of our friends; and touching the other, whom you call our Siſter,
I am verily perſwaded ſhee never was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged as ſuch a one by our
friends neither.</p>
            <p>Note here Reader, that albeit ſo many evil eyes do ſo
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently watch for our haultings; yet the accuſer was fain (when he had
objected one trifle done at <hi>Exeter</hi>) to go as far as
<hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for a nother. Thus is the charge not only repelled,
but turned even greatly to our commendation and praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>74</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> "Whether thoſe
that profeſſe ſuch Doctrines men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>S.</hi> 3. 3. before, and are
guilty of ſuch practices as are not to be once named amongſt us
[<hi>Anſ.</hi> No? what think ye then, of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> and
of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet? for all theſe did go naked; and that a far
longer time, then thoſe above named are ſaid to have done: Is it long of
your ſuper-excellent holyneſſe, and purity of mind, that ſuch things as
were done in the ſtate of Innocency, &amp; by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of Prophets,
would yet annoy your eares, if they were but named amongſt you?] ("as we have
them quoted in <hi>Fords Anſwer to Speed</hi>) will ſtand with that
Innocency <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Read <hi>Speeds</hi> reply to <hi>Fords
Anſwer</hi> and thou ſhalt finde his refuge of lyes to be ſwept away: But
what kinde of proofe is this? One of you invents a crime againſt us; then
reports it to another, or prints it himſelf, and ever after this ſerves for
Iudicial evidence, whenever you have occaſion to uſe it. And generally
concerning ſuch accuſations and crimes, as were objected or witneſſed
againſt our friends by any of the mercenary Teachers, this I ſay, and
admoniſh, that<pb n="53" facs="tcp:118999:29"/>as their teſtimonies and authorities are
not to be regarded, much leſſe believed; becauſe ſuch men are both our
mortal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and alſo parties themſelves, in moſt the
controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and conteſts wherein we are engaged. This <hi>Ford</hi> is
the man, of whom when he lived in the Weſtern parts, this jeſt was carried
about, <hi>viz.</hi> That he had ſtolen the Biſhops Lawn Sleeves, to make
him boot-hoſe topps of; [then was he noted of pride.] I have alſo ſince
heard of him, that he is a very troubleſom man to his Pariſhioners, in
exacting of tythes: [here he is taxed of covetouſneſſe, and of
cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.] Mark now Reader what kinde of men they be, that witneſſe
againſt us. For thou maiſt gheſſe the Lyon by his paw, (as the ſaying
is.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>75</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether though all
inordinate care concerning the things of this life be a ſin; yet all holy
carefull duties to preſerve our lives be not our duty? <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.28.
<hi>Gen.</hi> 30.30. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Call ye theſe <hi>holy carefull Studies</hi> to
preſerve your lives, namely, to begg of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> or
<hi>Patron</hi> power to receive 100. or 200.<hi>
                  <abbr>l.</abbr> per
Annum,</hi> for preaching the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinations of your brain? To caſt men into
priſon, and be but for 12<abbr>d.</abbr>? To begger your Neighbors (whom you
ought to love better) with long and coſtly ſuits at the Law, and that upon
falſe pretexts, (as is afore ſhewn:) To 
<note n="†" place="margin">See I <hi>Benſons book
hereof.</hi>
               </note> diſtrain their goods and take much more then ye claim? To
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a ſupplement of Augmentations, though yee had a ſufficient, yea,
many times a large maintenance before? to ſeek Annexation of another neighbor
Benefice, to that you had before, if your friends ſhall but eſtimate it
within a 100<abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>per annum;</hi> (though it happen many times to
be more worth) which practiſe heretofore in the Epiſcopal Clergy, was even
by the men of your own Sect, greivouſly cenſured and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: I ſay,
are ſuch as theſe your <hi>holy careful Studies</hi> to preſerve your
lives? What could the very Heathen have done more in point of
ſelf-preſervation, then you have done? Even ſuch <hi>holy careful
duties</hi> as theſe, were thoſe of <hi>Micah's</hi> Prieſts and
Prophets, (ch. 3. Verſ. 11.) <hi>Iſaiah's</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<pb n="54" facs="tcp:118999:30"/>&amp; <hi>Ieremiah's,</hi> &amp; finally <hi>Peter</hi> &amp;
<hi>Iudes</hi> falſe Teachers, murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers &amp; complainers, &amp;c. did
practice like <hi>holy careful Studies to preſerve their lives;</hi> Where at
length may we find thoſe Belly-Gods (<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19) if theſe be not
they? where them that mind earthly things, if not here? Would it ſeem here,
Reader, to have ought of the nature or likeneſſe of a Slander, to call
ſuch men as theſe be, Hireling Shepherds, and ravening wolves and greedy
Doggs, that never can have enough? And yet will they ſay they be reviled as
oft as they be ſo called? As if it implied no inconvenience at all, to be
counted true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, and at the ſame time to be the Devils
Servants, in doing all manner of ſin? I ſay moreover, that they that are
<hi>holy,</hi> do caſt their care on the Lord, who careth for them; and they
that will ſave or preſerve their lives, ſhall loſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>76</label>
               <hi>T: L.</hi> Whether the
penalty of not eating be not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on thoſe that are Idlers in
Gods Vineyard, and on ſuch of your partie as wander and labor not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw:</hi> The penalty of not eating partaineth to them all,
whatſoever they be, who being whole and able of body, and ſpeciallie
wanting food &amp; rayment of their own, do yet think it matter of fowl
diſgrace to them, to work in ſome honeſt calling, (though <hi>Paul</hi>
and other Miniſters ſo have done;) but choſe rather to live after the
manner of <hi>Drones,</hi> by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the fruits of others labors and
coſt; like as did alſo their Predeceſſors, the falſe Prieſts and
Prophets of old time, <hi>who did eat of the fat and cloth themſelves with
the wool, not ſparing the flock, Ezek</hi> 34.3:</p>
            <p>As concerning thoſe of our partie, name who they be that wander
and labor not. Wnder indeed did the Saints and Miniſters of God in old times,
and that very 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <bibl>Heb. 11.9</bibl>
               </note> poorely
arrayed; and not ſate they ſtill in a 
<note n="†" place="margin">Wander indeed they might, &amp;
that long enough be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore they found it too.</note> fat Benefice, in the glory
of the world and the friendſhip thereof; as the Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of
<hi>Mammon</hi> in theſe times do. Of theſe things alſo elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>77</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether there is
no labor but that which is handy &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> With you it is ſome labor to invent and write
your<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118999:30"/>Sermons, which after ye may recite to the people for
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or moneys-worth: a practice utterly unknown to the ancient Miniſters
of the Goſpel; ſave what they had read in the old Teſtament, touching the
falſe Prieſts and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets there reproved for this very cauſe</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>78</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> And whether hath
not the mind its labor, and that even to defatigation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Think ye that <hi>Paul, Silvanus,</hi> and
<hi>Timotheus,</hi> with the reſt of Chriſts true Miniſters, went not
ſo far in the labor and travell of the mind, as any of you? And yet for all
this did they not omit, much leſſe did they ſcorn to labor with the body
alſo, for ſuſtenance of the outward life, (as none of you ordinarily do.)
Of this more at large elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>79</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether
<hi>Paul</hi> doth not judge labouring in the word and Doctrine to be labor, 1
<hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. And our Saviour ſaith <hi>The Laborer is worthy of his
hire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though <hi>Paul</hi> did indeed ſo judge, as is
ſuppoſed in this quere; yet letted not this, but that he uſed handy
la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor too, and that night and day, earneſtly preſſing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing,
withall, other Miniſters to follow ſuch his example: For our Saviours
ſaying (cited in the quere) it is plain, that he here, by alluding to (or
alleadging) the caſe or right of a laborer in reſpect of his hire (as being
a maſter notorious and of all men confeſſed,) inſinuates only the like
equity and reaſonableneſs of his Apoſtles taking neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſupply
of food and rayment of them they ſhould Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to in the Goſpel: There
being a certain portion and parity of reaſon between the one &amp; the other
in this behalf: And in no wiſe doth he mean or imply, that his Apoſtles
ſhould or might lawfully be hired, (even as a laborer) to preach for money,
or like reward; or that they might or would preach and teach for ſake of the
ſame; for ſo ſhould he altogether croſs and oppugne, aſwell what
himſelfe hath ſaid, (<hi>Iohn</hi> 10.) by way of noting and condemning the
Hireling Sheepherd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as alſo the many and vehement teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies born
againſt this <hi>mercenary Teaching,</hi> by the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets 
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118999:31"/>and his own Apoſtles. But were the matter even ſo here
as the <hi>Quere</hi> ſeemeth to take it; yet ought the laborer in ſuch
caſe to require &amp; take his hire of them who hire him, for whom and to
whoſe benefit he laboreth; and not of others, who hire him not; who refuſe,
reject, and deteſt, both his labor as vain and fruitleſs, and himſelfe as
a counterfeit and deceiver. See alſo, §8.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>81</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> Whether Miniſters
are not to give attendance to reading, to meditate on thoſe things? And
whether 'tis poſſible for them ſo to do, at leaſt, to give themſelves
wholly to them, and yet follow handy labor? 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Both <hi>Paul</hi> that ſo adviſeth, and
<hi>Timothy</hi> ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed did yet (notwithſtanding their many travels
&amp; offices pertaining to their Miniſtry, and the meet diſcharge thereof)
<hi>work with labor and travel night and day, that they might not be chargable
to any, &amp;c. And this</hi> (<hi>beſide</hi> other cauſes) <hi>To make
themſelves an enſample to others to follow them &amp;c.</hi> (Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
not excepted) with this command alſo, or <hi>penalty</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>That
if any would not work, neither ſhould he eat.</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they note
ſuch as walk diſorderly, not working at all, whom they <hi>command and
exhort by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that with quietneſſe they work and eat
their own bread,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.7.8.9.10.11.12. By theſe
things it doth appear, how much <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> whom yet
you have avouched for your <hi>Patrons,</hi> do befriend your idle cauſe. See
elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>82</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether Paſtors
and Teachers are not to waite on their office? and whether handy labor be not a
means of diſtraction and hindrance to the laboring in the word and Doctrine,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Did not <hi>Paul, Sylvanus, Timotheus,</hi> and
the reſt laudably waite on their office? yea; did they not better waite on
their office then the beſt among you? And yet did they (this
notwithſtanding) put their hands to labor, as is a foreſaid. Neither is
ſuch handy labor more a diſtrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and hindrance, to Chriſts true
Miniſters now, then it heretofore was. But and if I ſhould grant the thing
to be<pb n="57" facs="tcp:118999:31"/>ſo as the <hi>quere</hi> would have it; yet would it
not ſtraightway follow to be lawful, that, to releive their neceſſities
ariſing by their not working and waiting on their office, they may begg, or
take a way other mens goods; eſpecially theirs, who make no part of their
<hi>Flocks,</hi> to whom they ſowe no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things, nor plow, nor
threſh, nor any labor take, (except to do them miſchief, and harme.)</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>83</label>
               <hi>T. L</hi>—Though they
had an extraordinary ſpirit to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Are there more holy ſpirits then one, as this
<hi>quere</hi> ſeems to imply? The Scripture ſaith, <hi>There is but one
ſpirit, Eph.</hi> 4.4. And again, <hi>There are diverſities of gifts, but
the ſame spirit,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. If ſo it be, what mean ye then
by <hi>extraordinary spirit?</hi> Now ſeeing there is but one <hi>holy
spirit;</hi> and this the Apoſtles had, let the Reader then judge what a
ſpirit yours is, which is not the ſame which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had, but
ſome other. Say ye that I wrong you by ſuch a <hi>Deduction?</hi> what
elſe do your words import? If the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had an <hi>Extraordinary
ſpirit,</hi> and you have not this <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary ſpirit;</hi> then
have you not the ſame ſpirit as they had, but either <hi>another;</hi> or
none at all: But if ye Retract, and affirme, that ye have the ſame ſpirit
indeed, as the Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles had alſo, but not in that <hi>extraordinary
meaſure,</hi> as they had it: Mine Anſwer then is; <hi>ſhew it by the
fruits proper unto it, Gal.</hi> 5.22. Alſo I ask, if your ſpirit be
<hi>fallible, or infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?</hi> If <hi>fallible,</hi> then not Gods
ſpirit, If <hi>infallible,</hi> How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it then to paſſe that ye can
neither preach, talk nor write without ſo many Errors, and contrad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctions both unto your own ſelves, and
to others, like ſpirit with you, both having and pretending? Doth this your
ſpirit guide and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct you what to preach? what need then of inventing
and penning your Sermons thus aforehand? Doth the ſame ſpirit ever move and
direct you to go to ſuch a place, or people? Whence is it then, that it moves
you never to beſtow your Miniſtery upon a <hi>leane-Beneficed
Pariſh,</hi> if a fatter may bee obtained? whence, that it ſtirreth you to
change Pariſhes ſo often, and ſtil for earthly advantage? Now tell us
which<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118999:32"/>of the very meaneſt of Chriſts true Miniſters of
old, did ever do any of theſe things: Of the <hi>contrary part,</hi> how many
of your number, even the beſt and greateſt of them, theſe things have not
done, and yet do? (unleſſe perhaps as to ſome or one of them there
lacketh opportunity or faculty, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requiſites for atchieving thereof:)
Now by theſe notes and arguments, (though there be many more added) it is no
hard thing to determine what <hi>ſpirit</hi> it is you are guided by; and
what is the god that ruleth in you ye ſons of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>84</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi>—Yet thought
it reaſonable on this very account, not to ſerve Fables, that ſo they
might wholy and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally give up themſelves to the Miniſtery,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtles (ſaith the Quere) thought it
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for Miniſters of the Goſpel, not to ſerve at Tables; I
grant that they might refuſe to do it.</p>
            <p>The ſame Apoſtles command <hi>&amp;</hi> exhort the
Miniſters of the Goſpel, to work with their hands; are they not here alſo
to be heard and obeyed? But the <hi>queriſt</hi> was ſomewhat over-bold in
this place, to ſet the Apoſtles againſt the Apoſtles; to oppoſe one
authority againſt another: To the reaſon of the <hi>Quere,</hi> I ſay,
that there is not the ſame <hi>Anal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gy</hi> or likeneſs of reaſon in both the caſes: For where
they command to work, they command even that which pertayneth to the
ſuſtentation of life; to the honor of the Miniſtery, and Goſpel, by
making it not 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <bibl>2 Theſs. 3.8. 1 Theſ.
2.9.</bibl>
               </note> chargeable to others. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, charity and
beneficence; ſeeing that by thus laboring, they may be enabled not only to
ſupply their own neceſſities but 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <bibl>Acts 22.24.</bibl>
               </note> others
alſo, that be in want Now in the matter of waiting at Tables, none of theſe
reaſons do hold place (at leaſt, not in equal bredth) nor yet any other
having par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allel moment, and neceſſity with theſe. So it will not follow,
that becauſe one of them may be diſpenſed withall, as to the Goſpel
Miniſters, for to avoid diſtraction and hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; therefore the other
may be alſo, for the ſelfe-ſame cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:118999:32"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>85</label>
               <hi>Object.</hi> It was neceſſarie in the firſt Plantation of the
Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, that the Paſtors ſhould work, becauſe that the Churches then
were poor, and under perſecution; but ſo it is not now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ:</hi> This reaſon is nowhere alledged in the
Scripture, where at anie time it is intreated or mention made of ſuch working
but other and diverſe reaſons, as both before is, and hereafter ſhall be
declared</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>86</label>
               <hi>T.L.</hi> VVhether theſe
words, <hi>Freely ye have received, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> give, Mat.</hi> 10.8,9. are not to be limited to
miraculous Cures, and onely to that extraordinarie time of firſt plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the Goſpel?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> 1. The Scriptures do make no ſuch limitation of
<hi>freely giving</hi> unto <hi>miraculous cures;</hi> nor do they confine this
<hi>free</hi> or <hi>gratuitous</hi> Miniſterie unto anie time at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. Theſe words <hi>viz</hi> Freely ye have
received, freely give, do relate to the Apoſtles whole Miniſtery; and
preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was a part thereof. Now they had a like freely received the gift of
preaching, as that of doing <hi>Miracles;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were here
commanded, to Adminiſter both a like free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And to heal gratis (like good
Phyſicians) and not Preach for money like bad Miniſters: Briefly thus;
whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thoſe Miniſters of Chriſt (as ſuch) had freely received
of Chriſt, the ſame were they alſo to give to others freely: The gift of
Preaching, as well as that of <hi>Miracles,</hi> they had freely received:
Therefore <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 3. The reaſon of the gratuity or freeneſſe
of this their Miniſtery, was perpetual, and diſcharged of all reſpect to
time or place <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For that, that Chriſts true Miniſtery
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways both was, and is freely received (without money and without price:)
Therefore is it alſo, and that according to Chriſts own mind and reaſon,
freely to be executed, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out limitation of time) With the like probability
of reaſon, (and ſame meaſure of impudence) may ye alſo except, and
ſay: We are not now bound to follow that Precept of Chriſt, <hi>viz. Learn
of me, for I am meek and lowly of heart:</hi> Becauſe (might ye ſay) this
was commanded at the firſt planting of<pb n="60" facs="tcp:118999:33"/>the Chriſtian
faith, when yet the embracers thereof were poore and perſecuted; at which
time it became them indeed to be meek and lowly; but now the times are changed:
Nay; may you not by the like way of reaſoning, or cavilling, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſubvert and vacuate the whole body of precepts, and directions contained in
the Scriptures? And ſo make them like an Inſtrument without any ſtrings,
ſave what your own ends and conveniences are pleaſed to give it to ſound
by.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>87</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether in this
Text our Saviour doth not only moderate the affection, and prohibit a mercenary
affection and greedy appetite of gain; and in the meane time permit to eat and
drink and take ſupply of neceſſaries where they preach?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, he
doth ſo: But permitteth them not with all to take from men, meat and drink
perforce: Nor yet to begg other mens goods of the Magiſtrate; neither to
ſue at Law, caſt into priſon, diſtrain <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as your
practice is:) Neither doth Chriſt in <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.35.36. (cited in the
follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>quere</hi>) give his Diſciples authority to make proviſion
for themſelves, out of other mens money or goods; but out of their own
only.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>88</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether requiring
that which is legally our own, may be juſtly ſtyled a coveting of other
mens gold or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Prove it to be legally your own.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Prove that it is lawful for Miniſters of the Goſpel,
to begg, and receive of the Magiſrate, a power to take other mens goods
againſt their wills, or indeed any other mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Magiſtrate hath no propriety in the goods of his
Subjects; but a meere truſt only, and that of well diſpoſing them for the
Subjects good and benefit, ſo as right reaſon doth require: Now it is
plainly againſt both theſe, that the Subjects, (many of them being poore
themſelves, and nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,) be conſtrained to contribute for maintaining
others unto all points of luxury and exceſſe: eſpecially being ſuch 
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:118999:33"/>as cannot plainly demonſtrate, that their Profeſſion
or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery do bring any good or benefit to the Commonwealth or people;
(but rather the contrary may be ſhewn:) See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing withall if they could ſo
do, yet ſuch over large contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions and allowances for bodily
ſuſtenance, would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to ſundry vices; and ſo alſo
leſſen and deſtroy the hope and benefit of ſuch their labors.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You covet Tythes, Glebes, Augmentations <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are yourss Therefore you covet that which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: (for
certainly theſe belong to ſome body, before they be given you; elſe
alſo the giver gives you that which was none of his to give)</p>
            <p n="5">5. You covet all theſe things without purpoſe of
render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for, or in lieu of them, any price or compenſation of equal value;
nay, or any value at all.</p>
            <p n="6">6. You covet more then is requiſite unto neceſſary
food and rayment, and the reſt uſes of life; which you ought not to do:
ſeeing ye both begg, and receive theſe things, as meere Almes or charitable
reliefe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>89</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether all the
Apoſtes did follow handy labor, or rather were not maintened by the Churches,
among whom they labored?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have ſhewed before that <hi>Paul,
Silvanus,</hi> and <hi>Timotheus</hi> (ſo <hi>Barnabas</hi> alſo) did not
only uſe handy labor themſelves, but commanded and exhorted other Paſtors
and Elders alſo, to do likewiſe; and that in moſt vehement ſort. And
though true it be, that <hi>Paul</hi> had power, as he ſaith, to forbear
working, and to give all his time to the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; yet did he chuſe
working rather; as preferring it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not working. And this he did (as one
cauſe thereof) to propoſe himſelfe an example to others. By like he did
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then foreſee, that in after times there would creep in (by fair words,
and the Magiſtrates power,) ſuch Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers into the Churches, and
obtruders; (or that ſuch men ſhould pretend to be miniſters of the
Goſpel,) as ſhould have hearts exerciſed with covetous practices, and who
would take upon them this office chiefly for gifts and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: 
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118999:34"/>And therefore againſt this ſort of men, it ſeemeth,
he thought it meet and neceſſary to fence, and ſhut up the office of the
Miniſterie, by injoyning thereunto, and as it were annexing handy labour,
well knowing, that now very few would be forward to undertake this office, (to
which no outward priviledges were annexed) but ſuch as ſhould be moved
thereunto of zeal and good will: And indeed this is one good
<hi>Criterion,</hi> by which the falſe Teachers may be known and
diſtinguiſh'd from the true</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>90</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether
<hi>Paul</hi> did not yeeld up his right, and wrought with his hands on
extraordinary occaſions, <hi>viz.</hi> to avoid the ſhew of
covetouſneſs; to eaſe the poor and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Churches; and by his
example to win authority to his command, concerning labour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If <hi>Paul</hi> did well to uſe handy labour
for theſe ends and reaſons, Why is it then that none of your Tribe do think
him a pattern worthy their imitation herein? Now <hi>Paul's</hi> ends and
reaſons for uſing bodilie labour, we ſhall here collect, and rank
together.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he might have to ſuſtain his life, and ſupply
the wants thereof: Here was he led by neceſſitie of nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That he might not be chargeable unto others: Here he
diſcovers his Nobleneſſe of mind, and Chriſtian amplitude.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he might make the Goſpel without charge: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
did his wiſdome appear; ſince to have over-burthened ſuch as entertained
him, might probably have frayed them (and others) from imbracing the
Chriſtian Religion, and have brought them into miſliking and
weariſomneſs towards the Planters thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That he might make himſelf an example unto others: Here
was his Fatherlie care, and the propertie of a good O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeer and Planter of
the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Becauſe as he had freely received his Miniſterie,
ſo he might alſo freelie give the exerciſe and benefit thereof; here is
his juſtice ſeen: He would not again ſell for money or price, that which
himſelf had freely received.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Becauſe it was more bleſſed to give, than to
receive:<pb n="63" facs="tcp:118999:34"/>Here was the happineſſe of his choiſe; with
<hi>Mary,</hi> he choſe the better part: Are not theſe ends, reaſons, and
motives all, both for nature, full of weight and worth, and alſo for durance
of time perpetual? Do they not alike obtain, and hold in all times and places
indifferentlie? Are they any part of the old Law? Are they typical, and ſo
out of force and uſe with Chriſtians?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>91</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether the main
grounds of <hi>Paul's</hi> forbearing to receive maintenance from the
<hi>Corinthians</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> were not fear of giving
offence to the one, that were very proud, and of burthening the other, that
were very poor?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Thoſe were neither the only, nor yet the main
grounds of <hi>Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi>
forbearing to receive maintenance of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> or
<hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> as the Reader may eaſilie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by reading
the places themſelves, where mention is made of <hi>Paul's</hi> working, and
forbearing to take mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, viz. 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 11.7,8,9 1
<hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 11,12,13. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.7,8,9,10,11,12. In theſe
two laſt places, the Reader ſhall find other ends and inducements for
<hi>Paul's</hi> and others work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, beſides theſe here ſurmized in the
Query, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That we might not be chargeable to any of you (which
yet doth not neceſſarily imply them to have been proud or poor.) 2. To make
our ſelves an enſample to you to follow us. 3. For we hear there are ſome
among you that walk diſorderly, not working at all (not working at all was
diſorderly walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) 4. And to work with your own hands, as we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
you, that ye may walk honeſtly towards them that are without, and that ye may
have lack of nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. But what do you ſay to the Elders and
Paſtors of the Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> mentioned <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17.
Were they alſo with their Churches, <hi>poor,</hi> or <hi>proud?</hi> And yet
even unto theſe did <hi>Paul</hi> in ſad and ſolemn manner commend his
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of handy working, not doubting to tell them, that ſo labouring they
ought to ſupport the weak, finally enforcing ſuch their duty, and his
advice, with the unqueſtionable au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Lord Jeſus, who ſaid,
<hi>It is more bleſſed to give, than to receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:118999:35"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 3. There are the ſame ends,
reaſons, and motives, why Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould now alſo
work for their livings, (if not otherwiſe hindered and with-held there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from
by their travels, and other imployments to which they be called and commanded
of the Lord) as in the Primitive times, (ſo called) if not far greater; for
there be now as proud, and as poor, as were then, for ought appears to the
contrary: Certainly in this one thing at leaſt, do the times that now are,
even far exceed thoſe in which the Apoſtles li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; namely, in diſputes,
controverſies, objections, and criminations moved about, and grounded upon
the idleneſs and avarice of them who are called Chriſts Miniſters; and
therefore were there no other reaſon but this, this alone were enough (if
they more regard had to their own autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or the honour and ſucceſs of
their Miniſtery, than to luxury of food and rayment, and other carnal
reſpects) to drive them to cut off ſuch occaſion, as afore is ſaid, by
work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with their hands, and abſtaining from taking even vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary
contribution; abundantly more ought they (for the cauſe above-ſaid) forbear
to ſue at Law, to diſtrain, to impriſon for treble damages, &amp;c. under
pretext of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent maintenance; and all theſe things do they practiſe
many times againſt theſe, for whom they never ſowed, plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, threſhed,
or planted a vineyard, being ſuch as do reject and diſown them, and never
did or could profit by them; yea, not rarely, even ſuch as live many miles
diſtant from them, whoſe very faces they have never ſeen.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>92</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether it hath
not alvvayes been the cognizance of falſe Apoſtles to pretend to teach
freely, only to diſgrace true Paſtors?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This cognizance had not the Prieſts and
Prophets, againſt vvhom the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> cryed, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.11.
and againſt vvhom <hi>Jerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ah,</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in ſo many places do thunder; and
yet notvvithſtanding they vvere falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Alſo <hi>Judas
Iſcariot,</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> together vvith <hi>Jude</hi>'s falſe
teachers, not only have not this cognizance given them, but even ſuch brand,
deſcription and character, as they hold <pb n="65" facs="tcp:118999:35"/>in common vvith
all you Pariſh Teachers; as face anſvvers face in a glaſs, ſo you and
they in every point agree.</p>
            <p>Were all the Prophets of old time falſe Prophets? and for ſuch
to be diſcerned by the foreſaid cognizance; namely, becauſe they preached
and propheſied freely? (without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and without price.)</p>
            <p>Were <hi>Paul, Silvanus, Timotheus,</hi> and the reſt of
Chriſts true Miniſters, falſe Apoſtles, and for ſuch to be known,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wrought with their hands, that they might not be chargeable to
others, and ſo make the Goſpel without burthen?</p>
            <p>But who ſeeth not how vain and ſenſleſs a thing it were
for falſe Apoſtles to pretend to teach freely, only to diſgrace true
Paſtors? Seeing they alſo that are, (or were) true Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, do
likewiſe (and ever did) preach freely. Why do not you alſo make uſe of
this ſtratagem to bring thoſe you call falſe Apoſtles into diſgrace?
queſtionleſs it would prove a matter of no ſmall advantage to your
Miniſtery; but no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſwayes ſo much with you, as love of
fleſhly pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>93</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether
<hi>Paul</hi> did not reckon his labours among his ſufferings and
afflictions? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Let the Reader conſider the coherent words and
cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the place, and he ſhall find that the word
<hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> there is to be taken for grief or pain of body or mind, which
a man is compelled to ſuffer againſt his own will or choiſe; and ſo
will the Greek word alſo very well bear to be taken, and not for a voluntary
working, which a man of his own choiſe uſeth to get his livelihood by: And
yet if it were to be taken in the Querents ſenſe, verily <hi>Paul,</hi> and
thoſe who (with him) were true Miniſters of God, did by this and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſufferings approve themſelves as ſuch, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 6.4,5,6,7,8. A
proof, which rather then the Pariſh Teachers will yeeld of their Miniſtery,
they will turn (moſt of them) once eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year, if the change of the Beaſt
ſhall ſo require; they can (if need be) be Papiſts one year, and the next
year Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, a third Presbyterians, Independents the fourth; like
white wooll, they can take any colour for worldly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:118999:36"/>But I have formerly ſhewn, that
<hi>Paul's</hi> handy labouring proceeded of his own choiſe and acord, and
that for very weighty ends and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>94</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether Chriſt
in <hi>Matth.</hi> 23 6,7,8. condemneth all theſe external actions there
mentioned, or the pride and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie which the Phariſees manifeſted in
them. &amp;c Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can you fix this charge on us, and prove it againſt
us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If you alſo (as the Phariſees did) do love the
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt rooms at feaſts, the chief ſeats in the Synagogues (or meeting
houſes) greetings in the Market, and to be called of men Maſter, then are
you liable to the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof, as the Phariſees alſo were: But now it
is manifeſt that you love all theſe things, why elſe do ye take them?
ſome of them alwayes, and the reſt moſt often; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch be
very ignorant of the temper of your hearts, as cannot perſwade themſelves
you would be ſore diſpleaſed, if you ſhould not be led to the higheſt
ſeats at a feaſt, or ſome other ſhould poſſeſs your Pulpits,
without your licenſe firſt obtained, or if men ſhould forbear, though out
of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to ſalute you in the Market, or elſewhere; or ſhould
call you by your names, omitting the title Maſter, is it cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, that your
Pariſhioners and others would be ſo diligent and regardful (as they are) to
ſalute you, to call you Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp;c. were they not perſwaded you both
loved, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for theſe things at their hands? (they do forbear to uſe
them to ſuch as they know do not love them) or that ye your ſelves, if ye
loved them not, would ſo kindly accept them being given, and that with ſuch
elaborate ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of your thankfulneſs, and being well pleaſed
therewith? What ſay ye to this, that many of your Coat have been known to be
grievouſly offended, even to rage and evil ſpeaking, when as they have been
denied the honor of any of the things aboveſaid? It's clear then beyond all
chance of a doubt, that men love that thing, and expect it too, which being
performed to them, they make much ſhew of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acceptance: and again, if
the ſame be withheld from them, they are of the contrary, much
diſpleaſed, and all of a rage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:118999:36"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>95</label>
               <hi>T.
L.</hi> Whether it be not as unlawful to call any man Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Maſter,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 23.7.9. and yet is not the word Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther own'd in the Scripture,
<hi>Eph</hi> 6 1,2. yea, and Maſter too, <hi>Eph</hi> 6.5. <hi>Col.</hi>
4.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I do not deny it to be lawful for a Son to call
him that is his Father, Father; or for a ſervant to call him that is
Maſter, Maſter; but if a man call him Father, who is not his Father, or him
Maſter, who is not his Maſter, do they not both hereby ſay that which is
in effect an untruth?</p>
            <p>Again, when a man entreateth of thoſe duties (or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
diſcourſeth of things) that belong to perſons, as they ſtand under
ſuch or ſuch relations, he is here by neceſſity dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to uſe ſuch
names or terms of relation, ſuch as are Maſter, ſervant, Father, Son,
&amp;c. ſo that ſuch uſurpation of relative names, which very
neceſſity conſtraineth unto, giveth men no warrant at all to aſſume
or require ſuch names between themſelves in ordinary communication and
talk, eſpecially when ſuch names are immediately given or taken; as
name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if <hi>Peter</hi> talking with <hi>Paul,</hi> ſhould have called him
Maſter <hi>Paul;</hi> a dialect and calling unread of in the later
Scriptures, except as it relateth unto Chriſt. Theſe are the words of a man
of great name; 
<note place="margin">
                  <bibl>Lud. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves. Com. in lib. 8. c. 17. Aug.
de l. Dei.</bibl>
               </note>
               <hi>Chriſt forbids his Apoſtles to aſſume the
name of Maſter, to ſit high at tables, or love ſalutes in the ſtreets,
and commands that the chief ſhould be but as a Miniſter; for honor aroſe
with heatheniſme, and ſhould fall therewith, and not ſurvive in the
Church, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>96</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether
Miniſters may as lawfully be called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as Teachers, <hi>Eph.</hi>
4.11. Overſeers, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.
Embaſſadors. 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.20. Maſters of the Aſſemblies, a wiſe
Maſter-builder?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It's a kinde of incongruity in ſpeech, to
call him Maſter, who is their Miniſter, that is, ſervant: This
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth your reſpective Pariſhioners, whoſe Miniſters you ſay you
are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. To theſe holy, wiſe, and ſpiritual
Miniſters, theſe names and appellations did indeed belong: But what is this
to your Fraternity? Thoſe you ſaid a little before, were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted
with an extraordinary ſpirit, which was indeed the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<pb n="68" facs="tcp:118999:37"/>ground and foundation that verified all theſe denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and
titles, above recounted, yet notwithſtanding was it not uſual for
<hi>Paul,</hi> or other Apoſtles, to whom yet theſe ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles truly agreed,
to be called in familiar conference, Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher <hi>Paul,</hi> Overſeer
<hi>Paul,</hi> Ambaſſador <hi>Paul,</hi> &amp;c. wherefore theſe things
make nothing at all to your juſtification, who require to be called Maſter
<hi>John,</hi> or Maſter <hi>Thomas,</hi> even in common ſpeech.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>97</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Did not
<hi>Paul</hi> exhort his hearers to be perfect? and would not he have bluſhed
to have affirmed himſelf to have been perfect? <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12 13. Was
<hi>Paul</hi> therefore like the Scribes and Phariſees, that ſaid, but did
not?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">This e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the blind Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts could ſee and
acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Eng. Col. at themes Annot. on <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12.</note> There
was a meaſure or degree of perfection, which <hi>Paul</hi> was not then come
to, toward which he yet preſſed, &amp;c. yet this letteth not, but that he
was even then alſo perfect, that is to ſay, in a lower degree: And thus
much in effect he bluſheth not to imply a little after, ſaying, <hi>Let us
therefore as many as are perfect, bee thus minded.</hi> See more of this before
touching perfection.</p>
            <p>Neither ought we at all times, in the things of God, to be
confined to the notions and definitions of men, but may warrantably ſo
underſtand, and uſe the Scripture words, as we finde the ſame words
before to be taken, and uſed in the Scriptures themſelves. And thus it
appeareth that <hi>Paul</hi> was clear of this Phariſaical vice, and
inconſtancy; it remaines now for you likewiſe to purge your ſelves of the
ſame, if you can.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>98</label>
               <hi>T. L.</hi> Whether there may
not be a lawful reſpect of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and degrees among men, without ſuch a
reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as is condemned by <hi>James, &amp;c.?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We blame you not for the very doing of any act of
kindneſs, love, humanity, nor yet for any modeſt and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſignification given thereof; but for this do we reprove you, and juſtly,
namely, becauſe ye make ſo great ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of reſpect to the rich,
as bowing, flattering, comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, ſtanding uncovered, &amp;c. whiles ye
deſpiſe the poor, howſoever rich in faith, becauſe ye give flattering
lying ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles<pb n="69" facs="tcp:118999:37"/>to the Great ones of the World; as
<hi>Worſhipful, Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, Excellent, &amp;c.</hi> Contemning in the mean
time thoſe of low degree. In ſum, your fault is this, That ye make not the
Image of God, nor any true worth or vertue (moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly) the
<hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Meaſure</hi> of that reſpect and honor ye do unto
men (whether in word or deed) but meerly thoſe things that periſh and
decay: Which while ye do, ye honor the <hi>Creature</hi> more than the
<hi>Creator:</hi> which is Idolatry.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>99</label> Concerning <hi>Pauls</hi> calling
of <hi>Feſtus</hi> Noble; It may thus be Anſwered, namely, That this word
proceeded from him upon an urgent and preſent occaſion, and that as a due
te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony and grateful acknowledgment yielded to the juſtice, moderation,
and fair behaviour of the man; ſhewed, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that his Controverſie
(then depending before him) with <hi>Tertullus</hi> the <hi>High Prieſts</hi>
Orator, <hi>Acts</hi> 25. The ſame <hi>Paul</hi> alſo call'd
<hi>Agrippa,</hi> King: being a title or name of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice (as well as of Dignity
and degree) and which truly did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to him as a modeſt confeſſion
thereof, and not in a way of flattery.</p>
            <p>Now the things that we reprehend in this kind, are, 1. The giving
ſuch honorable titles and nominal additions to men to whom they be not truly
competible: And this is a <hi>Lye.</hi> 2. The giving or uſing theſe ſame
in ordinary ſpeech, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the men themſelves, or of them: And this
is <hi>Flattery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>100</label> Neither is it in any wiſe
incongruous to our manners or judgment, To call, affirm, or confeſſe to be
<hi>Kings, Lords, Noble, Excellent,</hi> them whom we know or judge to be
ſuch: But we may not ſo do, when the title, teſtimony, ſtile, &amp;c.
do lack foundation of truth: Neither yet can we uſe theſe words in a way of
Flattery, without all neceſſity, or occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on leading thereto; ſo as if
the name of the man had <hi>eſpouſed</hi> ſuch <hi>title</hi> or
<hi>addition,</hi> and with it were inſeparably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned.</p>
            <p>But how came it to paſſe, thou couldſt find no titles of
ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor given to the Saints, as ſuch? The Scriptures call them Kings,
Prieſts, Sons of God, joynt-heirs with Chriſt, &amp;c.<pb n="70" facs="tcp:118999:38"/>And all theſe things are moſt truly and excellency ſaid of them;
yet notwithſtanding it would be ridiculous to call a Saint in ordinary talk,
<hi>King John, Prieſt John, Son of God John, &amp;c.</hi> or after this
manner to ſtile or write them in Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Charters, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>They who expect or require from others titles of honor and
ſuperiority, do plainly bewray a proud and Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſpirit: And
Chriſt himſelf hath openly forbidden ſuch affection; ſaying,
<hi>Matth.</hi> 23.10,11. <hi>Neither be called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for one is your
Maſter, even Chriſt: But he that is greateſt among you ſhall be your
Servant; and whoſoever ſhall exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall be abaſed.</hi> Now
if it be unlawful to Chriſtian men to affect any greatneſſe or
exhaltation above their Brethren, it can be no leſſe unlawful to affect or
expect the names or words by which ſuch greatneſſe or exaltation is
ſignified and confeſſed.</p>
            <p>And is it not of equal vice and unlawfulneſſe to affect or
aſſume the title of Maſter on a <hi>Civil</hi> account, as upon a
<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious?</hi> Seeing the reaſon or ground that makes the former
unlawful, is equally found in the latter: namely, Haughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mind,
and love of pre-eminence.</p>
            <p>But how fully and cleerly doth Chriſt determine this
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, and put the matter quite out of doubt, when he ſaith,
<hi>How can ye believe, that receive honor one of another, and ſeek not the
honor which cometh of God only?</hi> Joh. 5.4.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">section </seg>101</label> There were in the times of
Chriſts Apoſtles they who ruled well, and who vvere in honour rightly
preferred before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and this yet vvithout being called, or expecting to
be called <hi>Maſter, Lord, &amp;c.</hi> at leaſt in familiar
converſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:118999:38"/>
            <head>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
            <p>NOW he that alone judgeth rightly every Cauſe, being free from
all byas of prejudice, or other effect, be judge between YOU and US, and let
him render to either accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their works.</p>
            <p>To the poor in ſpirit let him give the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, while
the rich he ſend empty awaie.</p>
            <p>The Mourners let him comfort, while they that laughed do mourn and
weep.</p>
            <p>To the meek let him give to inherit the Earth, while with the
froward he deal perverſlie.</p>
            <p>Fill he them that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe;
while they that ſeemed to themſelves to be full, repent of their error in
famine real.</p>
            <p>Let the merciful, mercy obtain; as for the cruel, with what
meaſure they meeted to others, the ſame meet he unto them again.</p>
            <p>To the pure in heart let him grant to ſee God, while the filthy
be ſhut up in utter darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Honor he the Peace-makers with being called the children of God;
as for them that accuſe the Brethren, and make war with the Saints, let them
alſo be called after his Name whoſe works they do.</p>
            <p>Finally, To them that thirſt after blood, let him give to drink
of the pure Wine of his fierceſt Wrath, till fearfulneſs and trembling come
upon them, and the horror of death o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelm them; till they conſume as one
in a ſickneſſe, and wear away from amongſt the living; till their very
Names do rot and periſh, and their memories be no more with men, except for a
proverb and by-word of infamy; except for a monument of His much-bearing
Clemency; except for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of moſt deteſtable wickedneſs, and the
dread Wrath of God revenging.</p>
            <trailer>Thus, thus be it done unto them, for they are
worthy.</trailer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 58. lin. 12. for <hi>Fables,</hi> read <hi>Tables.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
